<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An account of the rise and progress of the religious societies in the city of London &amp;c. and of the endeavours for reformation of manners which have been made therein / by Josiah Woodward.</title>
            <author>Woodward, Josiah, 1660-1712.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 209 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 109 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67008</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">8794094</idno>
  <idno type="VID">41862</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248499969</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3511</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25214</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">08794094</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67008)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41862)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1272:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An account of the rise and progress of the religious societies in the city of London &amp;c. and of the endeavours for reformation of manners which have been made therein / by Josiah Woodward.</title>
                  <author>Woodward, Josiah, 1660-1712.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>Second edition enlarged.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>214, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.D. for the author and sold by Ra. Simpson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Christianity --  England --  London.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">London (England) --  Social conditions.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41862:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41862:1"/>
            <p>An Account of the RISE and PROGRESS OF THE <hi>Religious Societies</hi> IN THE CITY of <hi>London,</hi> &amp;c. And of the Endeavours for <hi>Reformation of Manners</hi> Which have been made therein.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Second Edition enlarged.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>JOSIAH WOODWARD</hi> Minister of <hi>Popler.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. D.</hi> for the Author, and sold by <hi>Ra. Simpson</hi> at the Harp in St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Church-yard, 1698.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:41862:2"/>
            <pb n="iii" facs="tcp:41862:2"/>
            <head>The Dedication, to the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens and other Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the City of <hi>London,</hi> and the Parts Adjacent.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIRS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I Conceive it very proper for me, and of the greatest Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to you, to lay particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before your Eyes those hopeful Means of</hi> Reformation <hi>which GOD hath lately pleased, in Infinite Mercy, to raise up amongst you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I know I need not tell you, That you are Denizons of a</hi> City, <hi>which for its commodious</hi> Situation, Trade, Riches, <hi>and</hi> Plenty <hi>of all necessary
<pb n="iv" facs="tcp:41862:3"/> Accommodations, is inferior to few; and for its</hi> Evangelical Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Liberty, <hi>and</hi> Laws, <hi>is happy above all the</hi> Cities <hi>in the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But I must in Conscience mind you, That all these great</hi> Enjoyments <hi>are in manifest Danger of being lost by those horrid Enormities, which have for some Years past abounded in this great</hi> City: <hi>for indeed they are</hi> gross, scandalous, <hi>and</hi> crying, <hi>even to the Reproach of the Government of your</hi> City, <hi>and to the great Dishonour of the</hi> Christian Religion. <hi>And therefore, I beseech you, even by your Hope of Mercy in both Worlds, that you would effectually set your selves to pull up those</hi> Pestiferous Roots, <hi>which will produce nothing but Gall and Bitterness to You and Yours in this Life, and that to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="v" facs="tcp:41862:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>AND I entreat you, with all possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Earnestness, that you would not trifle nor deliberate long in a Case of such absolute Necessity, but set to it with as much Earnestness and Assidu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity as you would to quench the</hi> Flames <hi>which you saw kindled upon your Houses (of which you above others have had awakening Instances) or as you would remove Persons infected with the</hi> Plague <hi>from among you; A dismal Case too! which you have reason to remember. And I am sure the least Measure of</hi> Christian Faith <hi>will assure you, that these are but some of the smallest Instances of the Vengeance of an</hi> Angry God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>IT greatly concerns us of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to look back, and take notice how many ways God hath tried us, both in the Methods of</hi> Mercy <hi>and</hi>
               <pb n="vi" facs="tcp:41862:4"/> Judgment; <hi>and how long God has suffer'd our perverse Manners, even till both the Providences of GOD, and the Sins of Men, seem to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced to a full</hi> Crisis, <hi>either for our Reformation or Destruction. And</hi> London, <hi>in particular, is many ways loudly warned</hi> to reform, that it be not ruin'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>HOW can you then, in Reason, in Policy, and in Self-love, (as well as in Conscience, and in the Faith and Fear of God) delay to take away the Causes of God's Wrath? How long shall those worse than</hi> Midianitish Women <hi>be a Plague and Reproach to your City? How long shall they be tolerated to spread their Nets in the very Streets, yea, before the Sun; and to bring their Rottenness into the very Bones of so many Persons and Families? How
<pb n="vii" facs="tcp:41862:4"/> long shall the Disorders of</hi> Publick Houses <hi>go unpunish'd, whereby many a young Man (that might have done good Service to his Country many ways) is utterly emasculated, and becomes feeble as Old-Age, and trembles like a poor enervate Paralitick?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>IS it not absolutely necessary to our</hi> Prosperity (<hi>as well as</hi> Salvation) <hi>that the</hi> Holy Name and Day <hi>of the Lord be sanctified, which have been so dreadfully polluted and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faned among us? And that every</hi> Family <hi>which would be thought de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sirous of God's Blessing, should daily seek it by solemn</hi> Prayer? <hi>And that they seriously set up Religious</hi> Hous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold Government <hi>within their Walls, as they would not be of the Number of those who disown all Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to God, and Dependance on Him?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="viii" facs="tcp:41862:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>VVILL you be discourag'd from this, because some distracted People will call it</hi> Fanaticism, <hi>and give it sundry ill Names, which the Enemy of all Goodness puts into their Mouths? VVill you be mock'd out of</hi> Religion, <hi>and the Worship of God, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises of his Favour and Kingdom, by such</hi> Unreasonable Revilings? <hi>Or rather will not every one that knows the Duty and Reward of a</hi> Christian, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice and glory in trampling down such puny Enemies of their</hi> Salvation?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>YEA, Let no Man's Heart fail him, tho he sees some</hi> Sons of Anak <hi>appearing as Champions in the Cause of these Uncircumcis'd Enemies of God. You may, in the following Pages, behold</hi> young Striplings <hi>going forth with a generous Courage against these</hi> blaspheming Goliahs, <hi>who defy
<pb n="ix" facs="tcp:41862:5"/> God and his People: And, praised be God, we have some</hi> Honourable Magistrates, <hi>who go forth as Leaders in this Divine Cause; and we hope they will at last smite</hi> overgrown Vice <hi>in its impudent</hi> Forehead, <hi>and cut off the</hi> Head <hi>of it by the</hi> Sword of Justice, <hi>since they go forth against it</hi> in the Name of the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND, O! what a brave and bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed sight is it, in these degenerate and debauch'd Times, to behold</hi> young Men (<hi>not led by ill Women to the</hi> correction of the Stocks) <hi>but lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to a just Correction! And to observe them taking greater Pleasure in</hi> Singing of Psalms, <hi>than others can possibly take in their</hi> profane <hi>and</hi> obscene Songs; <hi>and in short, better pleased in the punishment of Wickedness, than the poor abandon'd
<pb n="x" facs="tcp:41862:6"/> Wretch is in the commission of it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND in this happy and blessed VVork you have in your</hi> City <hi>some of almost all</hi> Ranks <hi>and</hi> Qualities <hi>of Men, effectually, tho secretly engag'd, thro the late Mercy of God to us,</hi> viz. <hi>Members of the</hi> Honourable House of Commons, Justices of the Peace, <hi>and</hi> Gentlemen; <hi>together with</hi> Citizens <hi>of all Ranks,</hi> Officers <hi>of divers Qualities, and</hi> private Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons <hi>of all sorts; So that you may have</hi> Society <hi>to join your self to, suta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to your respective Quality and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, be it what it will: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore every Inhabitant of this</hi> great City <hi>has at this day a most valuable Opportunity of doing great Service to</hi> God <hi>and his</hi> Country, <hi>of what Quality or Capacity soever he be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND shall I now need to ask you
<pb n="xi" facs="tcp:41862:6"/> what you resolve to do in this matter? Or which side you will take in this Strife, betwixt the</hi> Kingdom of God, <hi>and that of the</hi> Devil? <hi>Dare you be of the number of those who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile, discourage, and oppose such as apply themselves to the prosecution of scandalous Sins, which are our worst</hi> Enemies, <hi>and sorest</hi> Plagues? <hi>Yea, can you be cool and unconcern'd in this important Affair?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I must tell you, That there can be no</hi> Neuters <hi>in this VVar betwixt the Prince of Light and that of Darkness. It is the known Rule of our Lord and Master,</hi> That he that is not for him, is against him: <hi>and,</hi> That he that gathereth not with him, scattereth abroad. <hi>So that your neglecting to oppose the growth of Sin, according to your Place, is a manifest
<pb n="xii" facs="tcp:41862:7"/> cherishing of it in God's Account, and consequently an Enmity to Him. And if you are against GOD, he will be against you: and if so, nothing in the VVorld can befriend you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>THERE is a natural tendency in Vice to ruin any</hi> Person, Family, City, <hi>or</hi> Nation, <hi>that harbours it. It engenders Sloth, Variance, Profuse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, Pride, Falshood, Violence, and a Neglect and Betraying of the</hi> Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Good. <hi>It dulls the Understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, takes away the Sense of Honour, dispirits Manhood, cuts the Nerves of Diligence, and destroys the true Principles of Commerce and just Dealing. And by these means it di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly tends to undermine and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the Prosperity of any</hi> City, <hi>or</hi> Publick Body.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BUT Ruin will pursue Vice the
<pb n="xiii" facs="tcp:41862:7"/> more swiftly and surely, because it is push'd on by the just Vengeance of</hi> Almighty GOD, <hi>the righteous Governour of the World; of whose</hi> direful Judgments <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on other Cities abroad you have been suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently inform'd of late, if you have forgotten the former Strokes of it upon your selves. You hear from</hi> Smirna, Jamaica, Malta, Sicily, <hi>and other Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that many</hi> great <hi>and</hi> famous Cities <hi>have been shatter'd and swallow'd up by dreadful</hi> Earthquakes; <hi>whereas the same GOD (tho mightily provoked by us) was pleas'd only to shake and jog us in a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry gentle manner by the same Expression of his Displeasure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>O Sirs! take the gentle Warning, and improve the Merciful Reprieve, lest His Vengeance swallow us up also, when He next</hi> ariseth to shake terribly the Earth. <hi>This is, in</hi> Duty, <hi>laid before you, by</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Affectionate Monitor,<lb/>
                  <hi>J. W.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb n="14y" facs="tcp:41862:8"/>
            <head>The CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Chap. I. <hi>THE Introduction.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. II. <hi>An Account of the Rise of these Societies.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. III. <hi>Of their Progress, and their real Aim and Design.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. IV. <hi>Of their endeavouring a publick Reformation of Manners.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. V. <hi>Of their Orders.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. VI. <hi>The Reason of making these Things publick.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. VII. <hi>The chief Objections against them answered.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. VIII. <hi>An Admonition to the Members of these Societies.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. IX. <hi>Directions for Religious Conference.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. X. <hi>Devotions suted to such Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Prayers for Families, for Seamen, and for young Persons.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:41862:8"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> An <hi>INTRODUCTION</hi> to the following Account.</head>
            <p>SINCE the <hi>pious Education</hi> of our <hi>Youth,</hi> is a Matter of the greatest Importance to us both in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State;</hi> and since the whole Hope of bettering the next Age, and of continuing the Mercies of God with this, depends upon it: It cannot be unacceptable to any so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Person to peruse a Brief Account of that which our <hi>good God</hi> hath done for us in this respect; to whom alone be the Praise and Glory of the whole.</p>
            <p>IT is the Observation of many se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and judicious Persons, that within the compass of a few Years past, there hath appeared much of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41862:9"/> the genuine Spirit of <hi>Christianity</hi> in many young Persons among us; whose pious Dispositions, together with their humble and inoffensive Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, have occasioned the Praises of God in the Mouths of many pious People: For, they cannot but look on this <hi>bloomy Piety</hi> of these Orthodox and sober Persons as a very seasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Blessing of God, to excite new Spirits in the degenerate Professors of our Holy Religion, and to antidote those <hi>damnable Heresies,</hi> and check that <hi>exorbitant Wickedness</hi> which hath appeared with such Impudence in these latter Days.</p>
            <p>WHEN I first applied my Mind to draw up a <hi>brief Account</hi> of these Things, (being led thereto by sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry moving Considerations) I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vised with several <hi>Divines</hi> and others about it; by whom it was generally concluded to be a Work that might prove serviceable to the common In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest of <hi>Religion;</hi> and might revive the languishing State of it among
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41862:9"/> us: Which as it is the only End I propose hereby, so indeed it is a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration that needs no other to se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond it: For, I know nothing more desirable in this World, than to invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorate a hearty Concern for Religion in it.</p>
            <p>AND when this little Narrative was drawn up, and perused by seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Persons who were acquainted with the most hidden Springs and Motions of these <hi>Societies,</hi> they attested the Jus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice and Equality of it. In particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, the late Reverend Dr. <hi>Horneck,</hi> (who had a very perfect knowledg of them, and indeed was an eminent Friend, or rather Father, to them from their first Rise to the Day of his Death) in a Discourse I had with him a little before his Decease, was pleased to give his publick Testimony to it, That it was <hi>a very faithful and modest Account of the whole Matter:</hi> adding, that at the first appearance of these <hi>Societies,</hi> they were lookt upon with Suspicion and Dislike by many
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41862:10"/> of our <hi>Superiors,</hi> who now (said he) upon a fuller view of them, do not only think them fit to be tolerated, but worthy to be encouraged; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding with his Prayer, (in that Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thetick and Heavenly manner which was usual to him) <hi>That God would bless and prosper these Beginnings of Reformation.</hi> This was the last Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course that I had with that <hi>Pious and Worthy Divine,</hi> who was (we hope) soon after translated from his painful Labours to Eternal Rest.</p>
            <p>AND since the first Edition of this <hi>Account,</hi> I have understood in my Conversation with many Divines in and about this City, and by Letters from the remotest Parts of the Land, (from Persons whose Faces I never saw, into whose Hands this <hi>Account</hi> has fall'n) that the Piety of many Persons, especially of the younger sort, has been evidently enlivened thereby; and that it had been read by many of them <hi>with a very surprizing Joy.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:41862:10"/>
            <p>AND on this Occasion it comes to be known, that in some places the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Scope and Design of these <hi>Societies</hi> had been begun and continued by se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral pious Persons within these three or four Years past, who knew no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of these <hi>London-Societies,</hi> nor had so much as heard any Report of them.</p>
            <p>IN a certain <hi>Town</hi> (which I omit to name) some discreet and serious Persons, considering the great Benefit of a strict Observance of the <hi>Lord's Day,</hi> came to a Resolution to meet together on the Evening before it, to enliven each others Affections to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Spiritual Things, as a meet Preparation for the Duties of the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Day</hi> following. And finding the great Advantages of this Practice, they continued it for the space of three Years; and then hearing what was done here in <hi>London</hi> so sutably to their Inclinations, they were sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized with Joy, and betook them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to the same Method.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:41862:11"/>
            <p>IN some parts of the County of <hi>Lincoln</hi> a most profane Custom had long prevailed, to spend the three <hi>Lord's Days</hi> after <hi>Lammass</hi> (and of late many before it) in Horse-racing and other riotous Diversions. This Disorder was endeavoured to be sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prest in <hi>Cromwel</hi>'s Days, but in vain; and afterwards by some <hi>Gentlemen</hi> of the County, but with no better Success. So that it had now for several Years been lamented by serious People as an inveterate Evil which was not to be redrest. But it pleased God this last Year to stir up the Spirits of the <hi>Ministers</hi> of the adjacent Parishes with such Zeal and Indignation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst this scandalous Profaneness; that they took their <hi>Constables,</hi> and other proper <hi>Assistants,</hi> with them, and appeared with such <hi>Courage</hi> and <hi>Resolution</hi> against this rude Assembly, that the whole Multitude was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aw'd and put to flight. So that on the next <hi>Lord's Day,</hi> where there used to be many hundreds of this lewd
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41862:11"/> Mob, you could only have beheld se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral devout <hi>Ministers</hi> with their <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stables</hi> walking their Rounds: Or if any vain Persons look'd that way, their next Care was to flee with such speed as might secure themselves from Apprehension. And it is hoped, that the same Care continued Yearly in this and other Places, will perpetually prevent the like Disorders: to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press which, they resolve not to be wanting, as a <hi>Minister</hi> informs me from the Place.</p>
            <p>THESE things, methinks, give us some Ground to hope, that our infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely Gracious God is preparing the way of a more general <hi>Reformation of Manners</hi> among us than is yet visible, partly by dispiriting and intimidating the Actors of <hi>Vice</hi> and <hi>Profaneness,</hi> who have heretofore been undaunted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bold and hardy in the commission of it; and partly by exciting the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of such as oppose our <hi>Publick Sins,</hi> even to a pitch of Bravery, which somewhat resembles those of whom
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41862:12"/> it is said in <hi>Scripture,</hi> That <hi>the Spirit of the Lord came upon them:</hi> and then we always find that they prevail, and came off with <hi>Victory</hi> and <hi>Success.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>SO that it is beyond question, That if such as are of Eminency in our <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> did more generally give their Publick Countenance to this <hi>Divine and Glorious Work,</hi> it would run on with Vigour from one end of the Land to the other. And how much this would tend to their <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and Glory,</hi> in that Day wherein <hi>GREAT MEN</hi> must give an Account of their Talents of <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> before that Righteous Judg from whom they have received them, is not to be express'd by the Tongue of Men or Angels: Nor on the contrary, can we conceive the <hi>Horror and Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion,</hi> the <hi>Regret</hi> and <hi>Anguish</hi> which will then overwhelm such as either drowzily forget, or cowardly hide, or basely misemploy these <hi>weighty Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>YEA, the Pious and Righteous Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41862:12"/> will not stay till the last Day for the Regard due unto him: He will be honoured and esteem'd upon Earth, as long as the Notions of <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Evil</hi> remain on Mens Conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and these can scarce ever be blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out. And the Temporal Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of such is now the more visible, since the <hi>King</hi> has given his Royal Word that he will enter the Lists a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Profaneness</hi> and <hi>Immorality,</hi> as the <hi>Generalissimo</hi> of those who join in this Honourable Work. By which <hi>his Majesty</hi> will appear <hi>Glorious</hi> in the sight of Angels, and of Men, and be beloved of God himself, who will not fail to <hi>honour those that honour him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND in truth, As the consumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our much desired <hi>Peace</hi> with our <hi>Foreign Enemies,</hi> affords us a favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Juncture for the Advancement of this Great Work, so is it a power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Obligation upon us to set to it in good earnest. For (as a <hi>Divine</hi> of ours seasonably suggests) it is abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely requisite to justify the sincerity
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41862:13"/> of our <hi>Days of Humiliation,</hi> and the <hi>Devotions</hi> thereof: in which, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing the <hi>Publick Sins</hi> of the Nation before God, and praying against them, we have so far engaged our selves to endeavour to suppress them, that we cannot recede from it without being branded with the most unsufferable prevarication with <hi>Almighty God.</hi> And it is not to be thought that a whole <hi>Nation</hi> can contract such Guilt and come off unpunish'd: For it is not the usual Method of God's pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedure, to build up and establish that People which dare thus impudently mock his Omniscience, and challenge his Vengeance.</p>
            <p>ONE thing more may also be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark'd from those manifold Combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of Persons, piously inclined, in various Parts of this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> (as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so in that of <hi>Ireland</hi>) namely, that it is not only requisite, but even natural for Pious Persons to <hi>associate</hi> with those of the same Dispositions, especially where considerable Bodies of Men of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41862:13"/> contrary Inclinations join together to oppose them. This was the first Cause which induced Men to unite in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Political Bodies,</hi> and 'tis this which cements them together to this day; which demonstrates the Necessity of <hi>Religious Associations,</hi> in order to a general <hi>Reformation</hi> of Manners, and is a full Vindication of the <hi>Societies</hi> hereafter described.</p>
            <p>BUT here I have heard some elder Persons object, That it is not a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per nor a becoming thing, for Youth to manage such Affairs as these; it were better (say they) and more seemly, that <hi>Hoary Heads</hi> should un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake this <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Honourable Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince,</hi> and then it would carry great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Reverence</hi> in its Aspect.</p>
            <p>BUT, I pray you, <hi>Grave Sirs!</hi> who hinders your Assembling and Acting in this Post of <hi>Honour?</hi> What, but your own <hi>Sloth</hi> and <hi>Lukewarmness,</hi> and want of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Zeal</hi> for your God, hath so long stopt your Mouths from rebuking of <hi>Publick Vice,</hi> and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:41862:14"/> your Hands from opposing it? If you will vouchsafe to pluck your Hands out of your Bosoms, and fight like Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant <hi>Captains</hi> in this Combate betwixt Light and Darkness; I dare vouch that our <hi>Young Men</hi> will gladly march under your <hi>Banners.</hi> But if you all stand idly and timorously, when the <hi>Goliahs</hi> of the Prince of Darkness come forth and <hi>blaspheme the Living God,</hi> and defy his Servants; have you any Reason to be offended against these <hi>young Striplings,</hi> who stand up with a generous Courage to assert the Honour of <hi>God,</hi> and stop the Mouth of <hi>Blasphemy?</hi> In this ye add the guilt of Envy to that of Sloth: and I admonish you to repent of both, and to act more becoming your Years and Vows, lest these despised <hi>Young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones take your Crown.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AS to others, who suspect these Associations for the sake of <hi>Practical Religion,</hi> as things of dangerous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequence, their Objections are parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly considered in the following
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:41862:14"/>
               <hi>Account.</hi> And in very deed, what Reason can there be to suspect Danger from such who manifestly and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessedly pursue the chief Ends both of the <hi>Christian Religion,</hi> and of all <hi>Civil Government?</hi> And who do all this in Methods strictly legal, and exactly conformable to the Constitution of our Government in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>YEA, since the Maintenance of the Authority of the Laws of God, and those of our Land, is the great and only End proposed hereby: I humbly ask all such as reproach this Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, and revile the Promoters of it, What it is they aim at in so doing? Can you say, that it is not fit that the God that made us should be served with a supream <hi>Religious Fear?</hi> Or, that we ought not to regard our Penal Laws against Vice and Profaneness <hi>(those wholesome Ordinances of Man) for the Lord's sake?</hi> Would you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade us to give up our <hi>Holy Religion</hi> to be mock'd and trampled on, as it is by those <hi>Blasphemers, Sabbath-breakers,</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:41862:15"/> and other <hi>lewd Persons,</hi> who are checkt, and in part suppress'd by these <hi>Societies?</hi> Have you the Forehead to tell our <hi>Ministers,</hi> that they may read the <hi>Law of God</hi> against profane Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every <hi>Lord's Day,</hi> and the <hi>Law of the Land</hi> against it four Times in the Year, (yea both these in the peculiar Presence of God, and in the solemn Assembly of his People) and yet do nothing in it, nor take any farther Care about it, but make the reading of both these Laws a <hi>meer Mockery</hi> in the Face of God and Men? Or can you stand forth and tell the <hi>Magistrate,</hi> That he is not to be a <hi>Terror to Evil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doers,</hi> nor <hi>a Countenancer of those that do Well?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>TRULY, Sirs! your Attempts of this Nature will be in vain, till you can perswade us withal, That there is no <hi>God,</hi> no <hi>Providence,</hi> nor <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to come. And truly it becomes all that are under the Sacred Vows of the <hi>Christian Religion</hi> to consider this in a due manner, but especially those
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41862:15"/> who have the superadded Bonds of other <hi>Oaths</hi> and <hi>Engagements</hi> binding them to a special Concern for God's Service and Honour, as all the <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates</hi> and <hi>Ministers</hi> of this Land have in a very tremendous manner.</p>
            <p>AND blessed be God, There are some of both these who heartily and vigorously engage in this <hi>glorious En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize,</hi> and who meet together at set Times to further it according to their Power and proper Place of act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in it. And if any can be content to sit idly in this Time of their <hi>Master's Harvest,</hi> or are pleased to deride such as set themselves to it, we leave them to their <hi>Judg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IN short, Tho the Assistance given to this <hi>Great and Blessed Work,</hi> be not so great nor general, as to advance it at present with that Power and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versal Prevalency as is highly desira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: Yet thro' the Goodness of God to us, there are so many Persons of various <hi>Qualities, Functions,</hi> and <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> who heartily apply themselves
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:41862:16"/> to it, as are not only sufficient (under God) to make it subsist, but to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail in a great measure, even to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spicuous abatement of all manner of notorious <hi>Vice</hi> and <hi>Profaneness.</hi> As it more particularly appears in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing <hi>Account.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> An Account of the Rise of these Societies.</head>
            <p>I Do not here undertake to give an Account of all the <hi>Pious Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship</hi> of Youth, which hath been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst us in time past, (which, we may hope, has been the practice of serious <hi>Young Men</hi> in all Ages, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all the too various Denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>Christians</hi>) but to give a short Narrative of the Original of those <hi>Regulated Societies,</hi> which are now (thro' the Grace of God) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spicuous
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:41862:16"/> among us for many good Works; and which (if duly encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag'd) may very much contribute towards the Support, Honour and Advancement of these <hi>Three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms,</hi> in Church and State; and yet are but too little known to very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny among us.</p>
            <p>NOW, as far as I am able to trace their <hi>first Rise,</hi> it was thus intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd by the Gracious Providence of God.</p>
            <p>IT is now about twenty Years ago, that several young Men of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> in the Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Westminster,</hi> were about the same time touch'd with a very affecting sense of their Sins, and began to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply themselves, in a very serious manner, to <hi>Religious Thoughts and Purposes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AS to their manner of Life before this, I am inform'd, That tho some of them had been guilty of great Lewd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and yet became very affectionate Servants of God afterwards, (even to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:41862:17"/> an eminency, in the Judgment of some, who with Wonder consider'd their <hi>happy Change)</hi> yet the greater part of them were such as had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd a sober Education, and had not shared in the scandalous and heigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten'd Enormities of these <hi>later Days,</hi> otherwise than by their having been too insensible of the Dishonour done to God by them. But they now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to look on their own and others Sins, in another manner.</p>
            <p>I was, about that time, made privy to the Spiritual Sorrows of one of them; who with floods of Tears la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, that he had not till then had any affecting Apprehensions of the <hi>Glorious Majesty</hi> and <hi>Perfections</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> nor of his Infinite Love to Men in his Son <hi>Jesus Christ:</hi> And that he had not before felt any just Convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the <hi>Immense Evil</hi> of every Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence against God, tho it be but (said he) in the wilful Neglect or Misper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of any Duty to him. But now he saw and groan'd under all
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:41862:17"/> this, in very sharp and pungent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions. And withal perceiving the universal Corruption of <hi>Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and the deplorable Crookedness and <hi>Deceit</hi> of <hi>Man's Heart;</hi> and with what a world of Temptations we are encompass'd, being withal be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieg'd by many invisible Legions of <hi>Infernal Spirits:</hi> When he consider'd all this, his Soul was even poured out within him, and he was in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of being overwhelmed with <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessive Sorrow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE Case was very much the same with several <hi>young Men</hi> at the same time, (as he then told me) some of whom had been greatly tempted by the Devil (that <hi>Murderer from the beginning)</hi> to lay violent hands on themselves; which was also (he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess'd) his own Temptation; and that so urgent and incessant, that Sleep de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from his Eyes, as well as Rest from his Soul.</p>
            <p>IN this mournful Season, these dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>consolate convicted Persons often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sorted
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:41862:18"/> to their <hi>Ministers</hi> for Spiritual Advice and Succour; betaking them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves in good earnest to the ways of real <hi>Piety,</hi> and eternal <hi>Peace.</hi> And it many times fell out, (as the same Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son inform'd me) that several of them met together at the House of their <hi>Spiritual Physician,</hi> seeking Cure for their <hi>wounded Spirits;</hi> and so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted a little Acquaintance by those Providential Interviews.</p>
            <p>FOR, alas! (<hi>as he suggested</hi>) there needed little other Language but that of their Looks to discover their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Sorrows to each other, (especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when they came prepar'd to open them to their <hi>Minister</hi>) and they need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no other Arguments to incline them to pity each other's Case, but to consider their own; there being a Propensity in <hi>Nature</hi> to succour those who groan under the like Miseries with our selves. So that by these and the like Means they soon contracted a very intimate Acquaintance.</p>
            <p>THE Benefit of Dr. <hi>Horneck</hi>'s A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakening
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:41862:18"/> Sermons, and the Morning Lectures on the Lord's Day in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> preach'd by Mr. <hi>Smithies,</hi> (chiefly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign'd for the Instruction of Youth) having occasion'd much of this hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Work upon the Spirits of these <hi>Young Men;</hi> they did more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly apply themselves to these Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines for Direction, who had been Instruments in the Hand of God for their Conviction.</p>
            <p>AND upon their frequent Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to these and other <hi>Ministers,</hi> it was advised, That since their Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles arose from the same Spiritual Cause, and that their Inclinations and Resolutions center'd in the same Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose of a Holy Life; they should meet together once a Week, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply themselves to good Discourse, and <hi>things wherein they might edify one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> And for the better Regulation of their Meetings, several <hi>Rules</hi> and <hi>Orders</hi> were prescrib'd them, being such as seem'd most proper to effect the End propos'd.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:41862:19"/>
            <p>UPON this they met together, and kept to their <hi>Rules;</hi> and at every Meeting (as it was advis'd) they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider'd the Wants of the Poor, which in time amounted to such considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sums, that thereby many <hi>poor Families</hi> have been reliev'd, some <hi>poor People</hi> set into a way of Trade suta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to their Capacities, sundry <hi>Priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> set at Liberty, some poor <hi>Scholars</hi> furthered in their Subsistence at the <hi>Ʋniversity,</hi> several <hi>Orphans</hi> main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd, with many other good Works.</p>
            <p>BUT they were not presently brought to those <hi>pious Exercises, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> and Things of <hi>publick Benefit;</hi> to which they are now, by the Grace of God, advanced. As no Creature is born in its full Perfection; so the improvement of these <hi>Societies</hi> grew up by degrees, by conferring one with another, and by their enlarg'd De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires of doing Good, as Occasions and Advice were offer'd them. So that I cannot but recommend <hi>Christian So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety</hi> with the greatest earnestness, to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:41862:19"/> all sorts of Men. It must needs be as useful to <hi>Magistrates</hi> and <hi>Ministers,</hi> in carrying on their arduous Work of regulating and reforming Mens Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, as daily Experience shews it to be to <hi>Artists</hi> and <hi>Tradesmen,</hi> who join together in <hi>Companies</hi> and <hi>Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> and find their Arts and Interests advanc'd by a multitude of Heads and Hands. So that we may very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly pronounce <hi>Solomon's Wo to him that is alone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THESE <hi>Young Men</hi> soon found the Benefit of their <hi>Conferences</hi> one with another, by which (as some of them have told me with Joy) they better discover'd their own Corruptions, the Devil's Temptations, and how to countermine his <hi>subtle Devices;</hi> as to which each Person communicated his <hi>Experiences</hi> to the rest.</p>
            <p>IT seemed proper, for the better management of their <hi>Common Stock</hi> for Charitable Uses, to chuse two <hi>Stewards,</hi> as the <hi>Managers</hi> of their Charity. And the two first Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:41862:20"/> that I find (after diligent search) were in the Year 1678, whose Names I have by me, with a recorded Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession of them to the beginning of the Reign of K. <hi>James</hi> II. At which time the face of the <hi>Reformed Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> being clouded, and all private Meetings suspected, some of these young Persons, not having digg'd deep enough to have a firm Root in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, began to shrink and give back, (like the Seed in our <hi>Saviour</hi>'s Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, <hi>which had no deepness of Earth)</hi> being afraid of the Jealousy of the <hi>State</hi> against them, especially when they saw the <hi>bloody</hi> and <hi>merciless Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions</hi> in City and Country, with which that Reign began, which dy'd it of such a crimson Colour, as ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd it frightful to many, particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly to these young <hi>Proselytes,</hi> inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that some of them forsook their wonted Assemblies, and getting loose from their strict <hi>Rules</hi> and good <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety,</hi> they grew cool in Religious Concerns, and alas, some of them
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:41862:20"/> grew loose and extravagant.</p>
            <p>TIMES of Danger are indeed Times of Trial, and many times of Falling; as it prov'd to the first Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of our <hi>Blessed Saviour,</hi> who kept close to their Master whilst he was at liberty; but when they saw him apprehended, and in the hands of powerful Enemies, <hi>they all forsook him, and fled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BUT thrô the Grace of God, there was not such a total Tergiversation among these young Disciples of our Lord; but on the contrary, some of them being encourag'd by others, who till then had not been of this <hi>Society,</hi> being also griev'd at Heart to see some of their Brethren <hi>turn their Backs in the Day of Battel;</hi> and being anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with Holy Zeal against the grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Interests of <hi>Popery,</hi> (which then appear'd not only open, but in Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, being promoted by the utmost Power and most earnest Zeal of the <hi>Prince</hi> then reigning): Being (I say) greatly moved on all these Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:41862:21"/> they took up a more vigorous Resolution than ever, to do what in them lay towards the maintaining and encreasing the Purity and Power of <hi>Religion</hi> in themselves and others. And seeing that the <hi>Popish Mass</hi> was then publickly celebrated, not only at the <hi>Royal Chappel,</hi> but in other Publick Places, they set up (at their own Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence) publick Prayers every Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at Eight of the Clock, at St. <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Danes,</hi> which never wanted a full and affectionate Congregation. And not long after they set up an Evening <hi>Monthly Lecture</hi> in the same Church, to confirm Communicants in the Holy Purposes and Vows which they made at the <hi>Lord's Table:</hi> And by this publick Lecture (which was greatly frequented) many were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed both in the <hi>Profession</hi> &amp; <hi>Practice</hi> of the true Principles of <hi>Primitive Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion;</hi> for they were preached by the most eminent <hi>Divines</hi> about the <hi>City,</hi> from whose Lips and Pens <hi>Popery</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd such Wounds, as all her Art
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:41862:21"/> will never be able to cure.</p>
            <p>IT was the Design of these <hi>Young Men,</hi> from the first framing of their <hi>Societies,</hi> to conceal their Names from publick Knowledg, lest it should seem to be a Device to catch the <hi>Applauses of Men;</hi> which is but a very poor Matter, an Aerial Blast, of little importance if you obtain it, and of which you can have no hold: and they look'd upon it with a just Disdain, in comparison with those <hi>exceeding great and precious Promises</hi> which the Unchangeable God hath set before Men. But they had now a particular Reason for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing their Names from all but their Ministers and a few Friends; for the Eyes of <hi>Papists then in Power</hi> were intent upon them, who (together with those their Undersetters, whom Gain and the Promises of <hi>Court-favour</hi> had brought over to their Party) pry'd narrowly into all they did; so that they saw they had great Reason, as well as the <hi>Primitive Christians,</hi> to use the <hi>Wisdom of the Serpent,</hi> whilst they
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:41862:22"/> as carefully retain'd the <hi>Innocence of the Dove;</hi> especially being in the near Neighbourhood of the <hi>Court,</hi> which was then fill'd with Foreign and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mestick Zealots for <hi>Popery,</hi> or with crouching false-Friends to <hi>Protestancy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IN this juncture, upon Advice, they chang'd the Name of <hi>Society</hi> for that of <hi>Club;</hi> and instead of meeting at a Friend's House, who might be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger'd by it, they adjourn'd to some Publick House or other where they could have a Room to themselves; and under the Pretext of spending a Shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling or two, they confer'd seriously together in the same Religious manner as formerly; by which honest Artifice they carried on their good Design without interruption, even to the end of that <hi>unhappy Reign.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND since I have had occasion (a few Pages before) to take notice of the Disputes betwixt our <hi>Divines,</hi> and those of <hi>Rome,</hi> concerning the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> I beg leave of my Reader (tho it be a little foreign to the present
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:41862:22"/> Discourse) to lay before him a most memorable Testimony of God on the behalf of his Truth, relating to this matter, as I find it related by that saithful Minister of Christ, Monsieur <hi>Pineton,</hi> who was a great and long Sufferer under the <hi>Papal Tyranny</hi> in the Principality of <hi>Orange.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THIS learned <hi>Gentleman,</hi> having related the deplorable Ravages made on the Subjects of his <hi>Royal Highness</hi> the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Orange,</hi> by the Arms of <hi>France,</hi> which at last advanced to the total Suppression of the Exercise of the <hi>Reformed Religion</hi> in that <hi>Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pality:</hi> He goes on (in his Book en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>Les Larmes de Jacques Pineton de Chambrun, pag.</hi> 9, 10.) in these words: <q>
                  <hi>Je ferois tort an Public,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
            </p>
            <p>In English thus,</p>
            <p>
               <q>AND here I should do wrong to the <hi>Publick,</hi> if I should omit one Passage which deserves to be trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Posterity. One of the forementioned Gentlemen (the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suits</hi>) preaching on the Octave of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:41862:23"/> their Holy Sacrament, in the Year 1678, challenged me in his Pulpit, to make Answer to the Arguments which he then produced to prove the <hi>Real Presence</hi> of Christ's Body, and to justify the Adoration of the <hi>Sacrament.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>THERE was one who gave me an exact Relation of all that he had advanced: But I made light of it for some time, and had no thoughts of making him any Reply, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenting my self to give Satisfaction to such as made any Report of his Sermon. But at last, seeing that he provoked me from day to day, and that my People desired with Passion that I should return him an Answer: I undertook one <hi>Lord's Day</hi> in the Evening Exercise, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute all the Sermons which he had made on that Subject. I preached above four Hours, not only in the presence of my usual Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but of many Strangers who came to take cognizance of this
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:41862:23"/> Refutation. I may say, that I put him into a furious Disorder, by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folding his false Reasonings and false Quotations. I overwhelm'd him with Passages of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> about whom he had made such Ostentation. So that going from my Sermon, he sell to tearing of his Hair, and said to a Gentleman of the <hi>Roman Communion</hi> now living, whose Name is <hi>Villeneuf: Alas! I know not where I am. Good God! how shall I be able to answer so many Quotations?</hi> Indeed he took sufficient care not to attempt to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me; but contented himself to make divers Exclamations in his Pulpit about my affirming, that the Adoration of the Sacrament was an <hi>Idolatrous Worship.</hi> And he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved that he might some what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricate himself from this Affair by this pathetick Apostrophe, which I give you in his own words.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>GREAT God! why suffer you your Worship, the most August and most
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:41862:24"/> Holy, to be treated as Idolatrous? If it be true (as these Ministers accuse us) that we are Idolaters, and that the Priests are Impostors, when they say that they daily sacrifice the Body of your Well-beloved Son; where are your Thunders? where are your Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derbolts, to crush these Impostors and Idolaters?</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>AND in the sequel, turning him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self towards the <hi>Altar</hi> where the Host was exposed, he continued his Apostrophe in these words.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>YEA my Saviour! I address my self unto you, to demand of you that you judg our Cause by some Miracle: If we are Idolaters in adoring your Holy Sacrament, make the Fire of Heaven to fall upon us, as</hi> Elijah <hi>did upon the Priests of</hi> Baal. <hi>THUN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DER-STRIKE OUR ALTARS, and then you will undeceive us, and perswade us indeed by such a Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that we are Idolaters.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>IT was precisely on the nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of <hi>June</hi> 1678, that he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:41862:24"/> this Imprecation. And just ten days after, namely, on the twenty ninth of the same Month, being the Feast of St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> being then upon Wednesday about 9 in the Morning, God ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifested the Miracle which this <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suit</hi> had demanded. The Heavens grew Dark by reason of thick Clouds, Flashes of Lightning shone in all Parts, Thunders roared with a very extraordinary Noise; and there was one strange Thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clap, whose shock fell just by that great <hi>Altar,</hi> towards which the <hi>Jesuit</hi> had directed his Apostrophe, and where the Canon <hi>Caulet</hi> then celebrated Mass. The Clap of Thunder threw him down upon his Back, it tore up several Stones of the Vault; and passing into the first Chappel which is on the Left hand of the Quire, burnt the Cloth of the Altar to powder, where one celebrated the Mass also at the same time. The Lady <hi>de la Pisa,</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:41862:25"/> who was on her Knees, was much hurt with it, and all covered with Dust, with many other Persons. They carried the said <hi>Lady</hi> half<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dead to her House, where she was speedily blooded; and the Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-bolt which was the Cause of all this Disorder, going forth tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row a Window of the Church, fastened to the Tower, where they laboured till the Evening to extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish the Fire which it had kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>BEHOLD here a very positive Matter of Fact, known throughout the <hi>Principality of Orange,</hi> and all the neighbouring Places there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about: Which ought to bring all sober <hi>Roman-Catholicks</hi> to a serious consideration of the Matter.</q> Thus far that Worthy Gentleman.</p>
            <p>WE here, behold a marvelous At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testation of <hi>Almighty God</hi> to his Truth, much like that which decid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Controversy betwixt the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet of God</hi> and the <hi>Priests of Baal,</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:41862:25"/> upon Mount <hi>Carmel:</hi> And methinks as all the By-standers cried out then, <hi>The Lord he is the God;</hi> so all that hear this marvelous Event, should not refrain their Suffrage for the <hi>Protestant Sacrament</hi> in opposition to the <hi>Romish Mass.</hi> Truly, the <hi>Papists</hi> have dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carded their Senses and Reason to all Intents and Purposes, if they take no notice of this: However, I am sure <hi>Protestants</hi> will, and therefore I ques<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not their Pardon for this Digres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion.</p>
            <p>AND thus we return to our <hi>Pious Societies</hi> where we left them, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, at the latter end of the Reign of King <hi>James,</hi> and shall consider them at the beginning of the Reign of King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary</hi> in the next Chapter.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:41862:26"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> An Account of the Progress of these Societies; And of their real Aim and Design.</head>
            <p>THIS their <hi>Constancy, Piety,</hi> and good Service to the <hi>Publick,</hi> in so hazardous a Juncture, made them more known, and much esteemed at the beginning of the Reign of King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> those cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated Instruments of God's Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, for the restoring our <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Liberty,</hi> when the publick En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments of both were just expir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>THE first Design of those who join'd in this <hi>Religious Fellowship</hi> look<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> no further than the <hi>mutual Assist anc<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>Consolation</hi> one of another in their <hi>Christian Warfare;</hi> that by their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terchanged Counsels and Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:41862:26"/> they might the better maintain their Integrity in the midst of a <hi>crooked and perverse Generation.</hi> But as their Sense of the Blessedness of <hi>Religion,</hi> and the Value of Immortal Souls increased, they could not but exercise Bowels of Compassion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards such as discovered little Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern about these important Matters. Which inclined them to endeavour, by Discourse with their <hi>Acquaintance</hi> in proper Seasons, to press upon them those <hi>Divine Arguments</hi> whereby themselves had been rouzed out of a State of Carnal Insensibleness. And finding that the <hi>Grace of God</hi> many times seconded these their Christian Admonitions to good effect, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came more habituated to good Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, especially where there was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny probability of a civil acceptance of it. Insomuch that at length they could not but stand amazed at the Success which it pleased God to give them. One of them (to whom God had given a very deep sense of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:41862:27"/> Matters, and a very moving manner of expressing it) had such success, that he had (under God) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced most of his intimate Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance at least to an outward <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>UPON this they made a private <hi>Order</hi> at one of their Assemblies, that every one should endeavour to bring in one other at least into their <hi>Society:</hi> which they did to good effect. For I heard a very <hi>serious Person</hi> bless God with great Affection, that ever they made such an <hi>Order,</hi> and took such Resolutions: For, said he, this put one of them upon Discourse with me about those things, which I till that time little minded; but now <hi>(said he)</hi> I can never forget them.</p>
            <p>THIS may recommend <hi>good Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course</hi> upon all proper Occasions in Company; which where-ever it is piously designed, and seriously per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, will be blest of God to more excellent Purposes than we can with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out trial conceive.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:41862:27"/>
            <p>THUS then their <hi>Religious Frater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities</hi> grew and increased, even till they became <hi>conspicuous,</hi> and in some degree <hi>famous:</hi> which still induced other <hi>Young Men,</hi> that were of sober Inclinations, to join with them; and as they multiplied in distant Parts of the City, they erected new <hi>Societies</hi> by the Pattern of the old.</p>
            <p>THIS conspicuous Advancement of these <hi>Societies,</hi> in Number and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, gave occasion to some mistaken or ill-affected Persons, to misrepresent them to the <hi>Bishop,</hi> as things leading to <hi>Schism, Spiritual Pride,</hi> and many other <hi>ill Consequences.</hi> And this made their <hi>Names</hi> more publick than ever they thought or desired to have them. For now they were obliged to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear and justify their Undertaking: Which they did in a very humble and solid <hi>Apology</hi> addressed to the <hi>Lord Bishop of London;</hi> wherein they hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly assured his <hi>Lordship,</hi> that their on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Design was to quicken each others Affections toward Spiritual Things,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:41862:28"/> and to quicken their Preparations for another World, and to this end to assist each other to live in all respects <hi>as it becometh the Gospel.</hi> And that they desired to prosecute this <hi>Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Design</hi> in none but <hi>Christian Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods;</hi> with due Respect to their <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors</hi> in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any cause of offence to any one. And, in fine, their <hi>Vindication</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd so Reasonable and Satisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; their <hi>Assemblies</hi> so Regular and Subordinate to the Publick Worship, and their <hi>Designs</hi> so truly Christian and Inoffensive, (all which was at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tested by several eminent <hi>Divines</hi> on their behalf) that his <hi>Lordship</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared himself satisfied with it: Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressing his Approbation in these words, which are highly worthy of the Mouth of a <hi>Christian Bishop,</hi> say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>God forbid that I should be against such excellent Designs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>FOR indeed, any one that peruses the Vindication of their <hi>Societies,</hi> which they drew up upon this, and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:41862:28"/> another like occasion, (the Copies of which several of them keep by them) will find, that they have given such meek and full Answers to every Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, that they have render'd it very difficult for any Lover of Piety, or any one that knows and desires the Interests of the <hi>Reformation,</hi> to make any reasonable Objection against their <hi>Orders</hi> or <hi>Design.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AS to that which is fear'd by some sober and good People, namely, that it may degenerate in time to a <hi>Sect,</hi> and introduce <hi>Division;</hi> be it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider'd, that as this would indeed be a very detestable Thing, so they have most industriously senced themselves against it, by their <hi>Monthly Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion;</hi> their use of many of the <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Prayers</hi> constantly in their Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies; their setting up <hi>Publick Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> in many Churches in the City, and frequenting them in great Bodies, where they appear a very devout part of the Congregation; and their utter disclaiming of all <hi>Schism</hi> and <hi>Faction;</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:41862:29"/> and finally, their humble deference to their <hi>Ministers,</hi> (without whose Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, no <hi>Rule, Prayer,</hi> nor <hi>Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice</hi> is allow'd among them.) I say, all these Considerations together, give any sober Person all the Satisfaction that he can reasonably demand, that there is no manner of Ground for such a Jealousie: For indeed they find such improvement in all <hi>Christian Duty,</hi> and such Satisfaction in their <hi>Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences,</hi> in observing the Constitutions of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that it is remark'd by some that have made a full enquiry into the Matter, that they could never yet find more than one Instance of any Person of these <hi>Societies,</hi> that have faln from the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Communion to any <hi>Sect</hi> or <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND as to that other dark and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Case of some of them, who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter an appearance of Zeal for this <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Ʋndertaking,</hi> and a temporary Partnership in it, have faln off to Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Vice: It is like the cutting
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:41862:29"/> off a Member to the rest of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; they consider it with piercing Grief, Affliction, and Indignation, tho it be no new thing in every Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of <hi>Religion,</hi> to have some <hi>false Brethren.</hi> The first Planters of <hi>Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity</hi> had reason to sigh over the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postacy of a <hi>Judas,</hi> a <hi>Nicholas,</hi> a <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas,</hi> whom the <hi>Love of this present World had ensnared.</hi> And I mention this, that every one that maketh Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>thinketh that he standeth, may take heed lest he fall:</hi> And that they may <hi>dig deep,</hi> and lay a firm Foundation in Faith, Lowliness of Mind, and sound Knowledg of the great Things of our Salvation; and that they be very strict in Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Watchfulness, and in Mortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the desires of Sin, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward workings of Corruption, even to their Lives end.</p>
            <p>TO fall from a <hi>high Profession</hi> of Religion, will prove a very crushing and dreadful Fall: And therefore let every <hi>Christian</hi> look well to the Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:41862:30"/> of his own Heart, that his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Knowledg, and Holy Vows, may not encrease the number of his Stripes at last, for want of walking sutably thereto, and of persevering therein.</p>
            <p>MANY of these <hi>unhappy Revolters</hi> from their former strictness of Life, are now not able to bear the Reproofs of their persevering Brethren; they shun their Company, they know not how to converse with them, and are asham'd to look them in the Face; and sometimes they pray them to disturb them no more by their Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions, since they apprehend all the Danger they threaten them with to be very true, and foresee their despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate End sometimes with a Terror not to be express'd. And their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign seems to be, to divert those <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy Thoughts</hi> as long as they can, with all the sensual Merriment they can invent. So true is that Observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, That <hi>Religion can torment those whom it cannot reclaim.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:41862:30"/>
            <p>O! how much greater Comfort is there in the <hi>conscientious Practice,</hi> than in the <hi>profane Contempt</hi> of Religion, even in the course of this Mortal Life! But who can express the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite difference betwixt them in the Hour of Death, the Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the state of the Resurrection, and the unchangeable Eternity to come?</p>
            <p>TO shun this fatal Danger of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postatizing from God, and reversing their Vows made to him; it is the Practice of all these <hi>Societies</hi> to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the <hi>Holy Supper of our Lord</hi> as frequently as they may, thereby to devote themselves afresh to their <hi>good Master,</hi> and to confirm their Purposes of perpetual Service to Him, and as a means of receiving Spiritual Strength from Him so to do.</p>
            <p>AND in order to their more advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Preparation for so solemn a Work, there is in some one Church or more of this City, a Sermon preached every <hi>Lord's Day</hi> in the Evening (by the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:41862:31"/> procurement of some of these <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties)</hi> on the important Subject of <hi>due Preparation for the Lord's Table, and a meet deportment after it;</hi> by which, great Good has been done, and a deep sense of Religion wrought in many Persons.</p>
            <p>AND by this their Care to acquit their Consciences, as to this last Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of our <hi>dying Lord,</hi> many of them have (by the Grace of God) at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to that <hi>excellent Primitive Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> of frequent Communicating with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out growing formal; not lessening due Reverence by the frequency, nor extinguishing the proper Exercises of <hi>Love</hi> to God, <hi>Thankfulness</hi> and Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual <hi>Joy</hi> at this <hi>Divine Sacrifice</hi> of <hi>Praise,</hi> (as some unhappily do) by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessive and unseasonable Terror and Dread.</p>
            <p>THERE is such Love amongst those of them that have faln under my Observation, that scarce any na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Brothers are so vigorously Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionate. I have often beheld their
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:41862:31"/> meeting and parting Embraces with Admiration; and those who are new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly admitted are soon contracted into the same Fellowship of <hi>Christian-Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IT is requir'd of such as desire to join themselves to them, That they give the <hi>Society</hi> a solemn Account of their Sense of Spiritual Things, with the <hi>real Motives</hi> which lead them to this Undertaking, and what they se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously purpose as to their future Life. This is many times done in Writing; and I have perus'd some of their Papers, and have found them pen'd in such an honest, affectionate, and undisguis'd Stile, with such pious and sensible Expressions, and in so modest and humble a manner, that they would mightily affect any Pious Person to read them, and move him to break forth into pathetick Praises to God, who hath given such Grace to <hi>young Men</hi> in so degenerate an Age.</p>
            <p>AS for the <hi>Reproaches</hi> which ill Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple cast on these <hi>Societies,</hi> it is what
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:41862:32"/> good Things and Persons have ever met with from the beginning, and must be expected to the end of the World. The Scoffs and Grudges of such People against any thing, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrate that there is Good in it; and indeed their Commendations may be look'd upon as an effectual Defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</p>
            <p>UPON such Occasions of Slanders and Evil-speaking against them, I have heard them exhorting and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commending to each other, the true <hi>Christian Armour</hi> of Humility, Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and a Resemblance of our <hi>Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Saviour</hi>'s Silence under Revilings, admiring that Divine Command of his, of returning <hi>Blessing for Cursing,</hi> and of endeavouring to <hi>overcome Evil with Good;</hi> minding one another not to make any mention of their being of such or such a Society, but to make their <hi>Holy Lives</hi> to testify, that they are real Christians.</p>
            <p>AND thus by exhorting and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging one another to Christian
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:41862:32"/> Duty, the Piety of many of them has appear'd very eminent and exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary; insomuch that it is evident, even to demonstration, that their Zeal hath in many Places given new Life to the celebration of the <hi>Lord's Supper, Publick Prayer, Singing of Psalms,</hi> and <hi>Christian Conference,</hi> Duties which were in many Places almost disused, or perform'd in a cool and languish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing manner.</p>
            <p>THIS is (as far as human Eye can see) the <hi>real and only Design</hi> of these <hi>Societies,</hi> who seem with one Heart to attempt, by the most pious and peaceable Methods, to put a stop to our overflowing Wickedness, remove our Plagues, and to dispose us into a Meetness for the Blessings and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Presence of God; by whose Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing they have of late Years so en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creas'd amongst us, that there are now thirty two distinct Bodies of them, within the Compass of the <hi>Bills of Mortality.</hi> And besides those that have been some time erected in the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:41862:33"/> University of <hi>Cambridg,</hi> and in the City of <hi>Glocester,</hi> &amp;c. there are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers newly formed, not only in this City, but in various parts of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and even as far as <hi>Dublin</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland;</hi> where from three or four Persons; with which they began, they are now encreas'd to nine or ten <hi>Societies,</hi> containing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout three hundred Persons. And they find such Encouragement there from the Pious <hi>Archbishop,</hi> and from several <hi>Divines,</hi> and other <hi>considerable Persons,</hi> that they have been a means of reviving a great Sense of <hi>Religion</hi> in many of the Inhabitants of that City, and have begun a very hopeful <hi>Reformation</hi> of Manners among them; the <hi>Archbishop</hi> having signed his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of their Orders, which are copied from those in <hi>London.</hi> And indeed all these good Effects were oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion'd by the Examples of the <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don Societies,</hi> and by the removing of some few of the <hi>London Associates</hi> to <hi>Dublin.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:41862:33"/>
            <p>THIS leads me to consider those <hi>Christian Efforts</hi> which have of late been made towards a <hi>Publick Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> of Manners in the <hi>City of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and the Parts adjacent, of which I shall particularly treat in the next Chapter.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of their Endeavouring a Publick Reformation of Manners.</head>
            <p>AS our sober Young Men found great Joy in the serious Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of their Souls to Religious Matters, and by the compliance of those who inclined to join with them in it; so were they not a little griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, from day to day, by the <hi>profane and filthy Conversations</hi> of such as proclaimed their Contempt of God and Religion in the open Streets. And therefore they long'd in their minds
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:41862:34"/> for a legal suppression of these <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Enormities:</hi> Of which they complained often one to another, and much lamented them in their Prayers to God.</p>
            <p>IT is true, the <hi>Christian Religion</hi> is the most mild and gentle Instituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the whole World, and the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lest of Mercy towards Sinners; but not to insolent and obstinate Sinners, but to the Humble and Penitent. The <hi>Gospel</hi> it self is Thunder to the impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and impenitent Transgressors, and the <hi>Lamb of God</hi> then shews him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self the <hi>Lion of Judah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WE find a couple of <hi>Liars</hi> struck dead in the place for their persistence in one Untruth; and another was <hi>struck blind</hi> for opposing the <hi>Christian Faith;</hi> both these by the Apostles of the <hi>Lord Jesus Christ,</hi> who has ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed <hi>Magistrates</hi> to be <hi>Terrors to Evil-doers,</hi> and to this end has gird<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them with a <hi>Sword</hi> to cut them off, where milder Methods will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim them: and he strictly requires
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:41862:34"/> them not to <hi>wear this Sword in vain;</hi> that is, that they be sure to make use of it as he has appointed them. And who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever declines this in proper Cases, under the pretence of Mercy and Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, does it to his own Prejudice and Ruin; like the Man that <hi>refused to smite the Prophet,</hi> when required to do it, in the <hi>Name of the Lord,</hi> who was <hi>slain by a Lion</hi> for his refusal, as we read 1 <hi>King.</hi> 20. 36.</p>
            <p>AND since the <hi>Magistrate</hi> cannot punish a <hi>Transgressor</hi> (with Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness) but upon due Conviction; and whereas few are so rash as to trespass before the Face of a <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Magistrate;</hi> it is absolutely neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary in order to suppress publick Sin, that such Persons before whom the Illegal Fact is done, take care to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the Magistrate of it: For the execution of Justice depends as much upon the proof of the Matter of Fact, as upon the execution of the Penalty of the Law: And where the Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, or the Magistrate fails in their
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:41862:35"/> respective Duty, Justice is obstructed, the Efficacy of the Law null'd, Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity cherisht, and the Wrath of God provoked. And therefore the Law of God runs thus in the case of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane Swearing, <hi>Levit. 5. 1. If a Soul sin, and hear the Voice of Swearing, and is a Witness whether he hath seen or known of it, if he do not utter it, then he shall bear his Iniquity.</hi> And the same must be concluded of other En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ormities punishable by Law, by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable Parity of Reason. For, if none gives Evidence against a <hi>Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressor,</hi> none can be punisht, and all <hi>Penal Laws</hi> are vain. Besides, it is one great Design of the Temporal Punishments of Vice by the Laws of God and Men, to render it ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious, and to bring Shame upon the Committers of it, as an Admonition to others, that all may hear and fear, and do no more such Wickedness: which End (where such Laws are not put in execution) is utterly lost; and the contrary takes place, namely,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:41862:35"/> the Transgressor grows impudent, and comes to glory in his shame, and hereby the Community is apt to mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the Nature of Vice, and to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire it.</p>
            <p>OUR associated <hi>Young Men</hi> had due Convictions of these things, and were sensible that it must needs be as great a piece of <hi>Charity</hi> to bring a profane Person by light and tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary Punishments to shun Eternal Torment, as to bind the Hands of such distracted People as would o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise tear their own Flesh, and be their own Murderers: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were ready to do all that became them in their places to check those <hi>publick and scandalous Sins</hi> which were become very <hi>insolent</hi> and <hi>crying</hi> in this <hi>City.</hi> They only wanted some Directions to manage this Affair in a due manner, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Law, and to be counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced by some <hi>Magistrate</hi> in a Work so proper to his Office, and so worthy of his regard. And it was not long
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:41862:36"/> e're a <hi>singular Providence</hi> of God gave them a favourable Opportunity to express their Zeal for his Name in this Matter.</p>
            <p>FOR, about this time four or five <hi>Gentlemen</hi> of the <hi>Church of England</hi> (whose <hi>Names</hi> deserve to be had in perpetual Esteem, tho I have not their leave to publish them here) salling into serious Discourse upon the melancholy Subject of the Iniquity of the Times, came at last to a most brave and generous Resolution to do all that they possibly could by the Authority of our Laws, to chastise and suppress those impudent <hi>Vices</hi> and <hi>Impieties</hi> which they saw very provoking in the sight of God, and very grievous to the Spirits of all good Men. And forasmuch as some of these <hi>Gentlemen</hi> had made the Knowledg of our Laws their Study; they collected an Abstract of our Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Laws against Vice and Profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and drew up such prudential Rules, as are fit for the Legal <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:41862:36"/> and Prosecution</hi> of such as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend against them. And having (in the Year 1691.) by the Motion of the <hi>Lord Bishop</hi> of <hi>Worcester,</hi> obtained the <hi>Queen's Pious Letter</hi> to the <hi>Justices</hi> of <hi>Peace,</hi> to act as it became them in this important Affair; and the <hi>Justices</hi> having made a very good Order there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, and the <hi>Lord Mayor</hi> and <hi>Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> doing the like: These <hi>Gentlemen</hi> caused Copies of all these to be prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and to be sent all over the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, at their own great Expence, and lodged <hi>Blank Warrants</hi> in many Hands all over the City, for the ease of Informers, and other Persons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned; with many other excellent Expedients to further a General Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, which surely is the best of Works: Of which one of our <hi>Pious Bishops</hi> has given an Account to the World, to the just Honour of these <hi>Worthy Gentlemen,</hi> and to the shame of such as have reproached and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed their <hi>Righteous and Religious Ʋndertaking.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:41862:37"/>
            <p>NOW, this sell in very fitly with the Dispositions of our <hi>Societies,</hi> who thereupon formed themselves into two considerable Bodies, for Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation against Publick Enormities, the one in <hi>London,</hi> the other in <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster,</hi> the better to advance this Work in all Parts, according to their respective places of abode. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they gave punctual Informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to some Magistrate or other of those publick Acts of <hi>Debauchery</hi> and <hi>Profaneness</hi> which they observed to be committed by Persons hardned in their Sins; still keeping to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the <hi>Law,</hi> and the <hi>Rules</hi> subservient thereunto which those <hi>Gentlemen</hi> had given them.</p>
            <p>BUT <hi>Wickedness</hi> being at that time insolent and unused to restraint, these Persons met with very outragious Resentments, and with bitter Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches and Threats from the pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sionate Lovers of Vice: Yea, they often ran the hazard of their Lives in the prosecution of this Design; which
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:41862:37"/> they underwent with Christian Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, being supported (under God) by divers of our <hi>Bishops</hi> and <hi>London Divines,</hi> who told them, That if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them suffer'd in so Divine a Work, they would very much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semble the <hi>Martyrs</hi> and <hi>Confessors</hi> of Christ, and receive the Reward of it in the other World. And in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect, the <hi>Right Reverend Bishop of Glocester,</hi> and those worthy Divines Dr. <hi>Horneck,</hi> Dr. <hi>Jekyl,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Stephens,</hi> have most eminently signalized their Zeal for their <hi>Great Master</hi> and his Work.</p>
            <p>AND whereas our <hi>Young Men</hi> found it very often objected in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Discourse, that they were only a few raw Youths that engaged in this Work, which seem'd particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly to exasperate the Persons prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by them; they greatly wisht for the concurrence of some grave and elderly Persons to countenance and enspirit them in this <hi>difficult Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:41862:38"/>
            <p>TO this our Good God, who would not suffer this <hi>Excellent Work</hi> (undertaken purely for his sake) to drop, was pleased by his <hi>good Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> to administer a very seasonable Support. For it fell out about this time, that the good Service of seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Men (most of them House-keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers) in the <hi>Tower-Hamlets</hi> came to be known, which was begun on this occasion.</p>
            <p>THE Inhabitants of those <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets</hi> being much perplexed by pilfering People, Pick-locks, House-breakers, and such ill Persons; some of them began to inquire into the Places which were suspected to harbour that sort of People. And by tracing out their Places of Resort, they soon div'd into the true source of their Grievances; namely, That these vicious Persons living in shameful <hi>lewdness</hi> and <hi>idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi> and having no Income by <hi>Trade</hi> or <hi>Estate</hi> to maintain them in it, they betook themselves to <hi>Robbery, Shop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifting, Burglary,</hi> and <hi>picking of Locks</hi>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:41862:38"/> and <hi>Pockets,</hi> to maintain their expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive Lusts and lewd Companions.</p>
            <p>UPON this, some of the sober In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of these <hi>Hamlets</hi> set them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves with great Concern, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted Courage, to pull down the very <hi>Nosts</hi> of these <hi>Disorders.</hi> They got <hi>Warrants</hi> for search, and brought all suspected Persons to clear them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves in a legal way, and where it was requisite, they demanded Securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for their Good-behaviour; they prosecuted and supprest all known Houses of <hi>Bawdery,</hi> and brought the Keepers of them to legal Punishment. And whereas some of those who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in this Work were of the <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Communion,</hi> and others of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent <hi>Perswasions,</hi> their lesser Differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in Matters of <hi>Religion,</hi> did not in the least divide them in prosecuting of these things which they saw were directly contrary to all Religion. And such as did not act personally in this Affair, yet perceiving the <hi>Good</hi> that
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:41862:39"/> came of it, were inclined to contribute towards it.</p>
            <p>BUT there were some things wanting in this Undertaking, in the defect of which it was much retard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and had like to have sunk. The one was a <hi>methodical way</hi> of proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for want of which their Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours were neither so orderly, nor so effectual as they afterwards prov'd. They also wanted a more compact <hi>Incorporation</hi> of their Members into one <hi>Society</hi> or Body, which might be moved and guided by the same prudential Methods, as if they all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from the same Soul. And lastly, their <hi>Fund</hi> was low, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sufficient to defray the Expence of such an Affair. For, since the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehension of lewd <hi>Ruffians,</hi> and des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate <hi>Bullies,</hi> needed a good num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>Officers</hi> and other <hi>Assistants;</hi> and since the Process of our Law is not a little chargable, it must be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, that <hi>Money is the Sinews of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:41862:39"/> his War,</hi> as well as others.</p>
            <p>NOW our aforesaid <hi>Societies for giving of Informations,</hi> having consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered these Circumstances, and hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing admired the <hi>Zeal</hi> and <hi>Courage</hi> of those honest and excellent Men in these <hi>Hamlets,</hi> and observed how well they suted to make up what themselves wanted in Years and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, they resolved to concur with them, that their <hi>united Forces</hi> might be the more victorious: And the <hi>Gentlemen</hi> before-mentioned gave their hearty Consent to the Match, and (like kind Fathers) did not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle augment the <hi>Dowry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND now their Resolved Work went on with happy Success, the one emulating and pushing on the other. And in all Cases they acted regularly, and in conformity to Rules approved by the <hi>Learned in the Law.</hi> They chose two <hi>Stewards</hi> to keep their Cash, and to keep an exact Account of all <hi>Contributions</hi> and <hi>Disbursments.</hi> They had a set place of assembling
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:41862:40"/> together, in which they observed a regular Method of Proposing, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bating, and Concluding every thing; and had a <hi>Notary</hi> on all Occasions to attend them: and finally, at this weekly Meeting, they concerted those Measures which they prosecuted with Vigour in the <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Suburbs,</hi> and with very great Success.</p>
            <p>FOR they were instrumental in put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting down several <hi>open Markets</hi> that had been kept on the <hi>Lord's Day;</hi> and in suppressing some hundreds of <hi>Houses of ill Fame,</hi> bringing the Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenters of them to due Shame and Punishment. And by the means of this <hi>Society</hi> alone, about 2000 <hi>Persons</hi> have been legally prosecuted and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed, either as keepers of <hi>Houses of Bawdery</hi> and <hi>Disorder,</hi> or as <hi>Whores, Night-walkers,</hi> and the like; and the Names of these Delinquents are set down in <hi>three black Lists</hi> which they have printed: All which have been sentenced by the <hi>Magistrates</hi> as the Law directs, and have accordingly
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:41862:40"/> been punished, (many of them divers times) either by <hi>Carting, Whipping, Fining, Imprisonment,</hi> or suppressing their <hi>Licences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THEY have also been instrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal to put down several <hi>Musick-houses</hi> which had degenerated into notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Nurseries of Lewdness and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchery:</hi> As it appeared by a Paper printed on this occasion, wherein it was proved, that many Persons had been ensnared by the rude Company which usually resorted to those Houses, to the Ruin of their Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; and some to that utter extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of Modesty, that some of both Sexes had shamelesly danced naked in these licentious Brothels; which Disorder had abounded to that degree, that above twenty Murders had been committed in them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a very little time. All which must needs render them odious in the Eyes of all sober People.</p>
            <p>BESIDES this, the Members of this <hi>Society</hi> have legally convicted
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:41862:41"/> multitudes of notorious Swearers, Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath-breakers, and Drunkards: and their Proceedings in all these Cases have been so strictly legal and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blamable, that they have for several Years past received great Countenance in the several <hi>Courts of Judicature;</hi> and have found very considerable En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement from the <hi>Lord Mayor</hi> and <hi>Court of Aldermen,</hi> who have honourably contributed towards the great Expence of so great and useful an Undertaking.</p>
            <p>BUT yet these Endeavours of so general a <hi>Good,</hi> did not proceed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out many a Rub; if it had, it would have been the first time that Vertue had been advanced with Ease and Smoothness. We must have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, that either <hi>Vertue</hi> or <hi>Vice</hi> had lost its Nature, if the one could sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plant and dethrone the other without passionate Opposition: Yea we might have thought that the <hi>Devil</hi> had lost his Envy to the Good of Mankind, or that all the Legions of the <hi>Infernal
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:41862:41"/> Pit</hi> had been cast into a <hi>deep Sleep,</hi> should they have suffer'd such a brave Onset to be made upon the Territories of <hi>Darkness,</hi> without making all the Interest they had against it. It was therefore no wonder at all, that the Undertakers of this <hi>Divine Work</hi> met with many Difficulties to strugle with in the Prosecution of it.</p>
            <p>IN truth, they experienced not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the rude Assaults of licentious <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchees;</hi> which they expected; but too often the Brow-beatings and Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement of such as were bound by the tremendous Bond of an <hi>Oath,</hi> and the Divine Trust of <hi>Authority</hi> to do otherwise, which was the more difficult to bear.</p>
            <p>I have known the Day in which several Persons have with extream sorrow complained, that they had spent above half of it in going from the House of one <hi>Justice of Peace</hi> to another, before they could get a Warrant signed. Such Complaints were too-frequent, and alas! too true.</p>
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:41862:42"/>
            <p>BUT there was great Hope of a full Redress to this Grievance, when there came forth a Pious Proclamation from <hi>their Majesties,</hi> Jan. 21. 1691 / 2. <hi>requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all Magistrates, Ecclesiastical and Civil, in their respective Stations, to execute the Laws of this Realm against Profaneness and Immorality, as they would answer it to Almighty God, and upon Pain of their Majesties highest Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasure; complaining also</hi> (most just<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) <hi>That by a long continued Neglect and Connivance of the Magistrates and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers concerned, these dissolute Enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties had universally spread themselves, to the dishonour of God, and the scandal of our Holy Religion,</hi> &amp;c. This Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation was occasioned <hi>by the pious Address of our Arch-bishops and Bishops to their Majesties,</hi> as the Preamble of it declares.</p>
            <p>AND since this did not fully ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complish its End, it was followed (<hi>May</hi> 16. 1693.) by a personal Exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the <hi>Justices</hi> of <hi>Middlesex,</hi> to further this work with Vigour, by
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:41862:42"/> the <hi>Lord Keeper</hi> in a Speech made to them to that purpose, <hi>by her Majesty's Special Command:</hi> and partly by these Supports, but chiefly by the <hi>good Hand of God</hi> upon it, this Enterprize has gained Ground, notwithstanding the many ill turns that have been done it.</p>
            <p>INSOMUCH, that there are now near twenty <hi>Societies</hi> of various <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities</hi> and <hi>Functions,</hi> formed in a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination and Correspondency one with another, and engaged in this Christian Design in and about this <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Suburbs:</hi> All which have their set Hours and Places of meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to direct, support, and execute this their Undertaking.</p>
            <p>IN this Number of the <hi>Societies for Reformation</hi> here given, I do not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude any of the thirty two <hi>Religious Societies</hi> before mentioned. For tho they all agree in the love of Vertue, and dislike of Vice, yet their first and more direct Design of Association seems to be distinguish'd thus: In that the <hi>Societies for Reformation</hi> bent
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:41862:43"/> their utmost Endeavours from the first to suppress <hi>publick Vice;</hi> whilst the <hi>Religious Societies</hi> endeavour'd chiefly to promote <hi>Religion</hi> in their own Breasts, tho they have since been e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minently instrumental in the Publick Reformation. The <hi>former</hi> endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to take away the Reproach of our Religion, by curbing the Exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitances of its Professors; the <hi>latter</hi> attempted to retrieve that Holy Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour in the Practice of Religion which becomes <hi>Christians.</hi> And whereas these <hi>latter</hi> are all of the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and fervent Lovers, and strict observers of her <hi>Publick Worship;</hi> the <hi>former</hi> are composed of all such as bear a hearty Indignation against Vice and Impiety, tho of different Perswasions in some Circumstantials of Religion. For in this Case, the Members of our Church do not say to any Lovers of Piety, as <hi>Zerubba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel</hi> to the Adversaries of <hi>Judah, Ye have nothing to do to build with us:</hi> For they consider Vice as an Enemy
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:41862:43"/> to human Nature, and as tending to the ruin of the whole World. We do therefore with humble Thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness to Almighty God acknowledg the Brotherly Assistance which is given us by some of our <hi>Dissenting Brethren</hi> (especially those of the <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Perswasion</hi>) in endeavouring to discountenance and suppress pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Enormities, which have been so generally spread, and so long taking Root, that they need the help of all Hands to pluck them up. And it is not only in <hi>London,</hi> but in <hi>Notting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Shrewsbury,</hi> and other Parts, that they join hand in hand with those of our Communion, in order to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press the Vices of the Place. <hi>It is God that maketh Men of one Mind in a House,</hi> much more in a <hi>Nation:</hi> and I beseech the <hi>God of Peace</hi> to bring all that sincerely love and fear him, to perfect Peace and Coalition: For this we pray incessantly in our <hi>Publick Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,</hi> wherein we entreat the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, that he
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:41862:44"/> would <hi>bring all such as profess his Holy Name to agree in the Truth of his Holy Word, and to live in Ʋnity and godly Love.</hi> When once this shall come to pass, we may hope that the Enemies to the <hi>Fundamental Principles</hi> and <hi>Practices</hi> of our <hi>Holy Religion,</hi> being <hi>covered with Shame, may seek unto God:</hi> and then (as an <hi>eminent French Refugee</hi> observed) will the English Church and Nation be thrice Happy.</p>
            <p>THESE Endeavours to stop the wide mouth of our <hi>crying Sins,</hi> have (by the Blessing of God) so far suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded, that the Impudence of lewd Women, and the Blasphemies of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centious Tongues are manifestly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated in our Streets, and the works of Darkness seem to be retiring to their proper Scene, the <hi>obscurest Corners</hi> that can be found, as most remote from human Observation and Punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>BUT the banishment of Vice from the publick View, is not all the Good that has been done by these legal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutions,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:41862:44"/> (tho that is most highly valuable, as it takes away publick <hi>Scandals</hi> and <hi>Temptations</hi>) but there have been many Instances of Persons apprehended in ill Houses and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; who having something of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>desty and Tenderness remaining, have been alarmed out of this ill way of Life, and have afterwards acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged the <hi>Mercy</hi> of God, and the <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> of Men, in <hi>pulling them as Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brands out of the Fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND indeed, since the <hi>Magistrates</hi> chastizing of wicked People is an <hi>Ordinance of God,</hi> it is scarce to be question'd but that it is designed for the <hi>Spiritual Good</hi> of particular Men, as well as the <hi>Publick Good</hi> of <hi>Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties:</hi> and what doubt can there be, but that God does many times turn such legal Corrections to infinite Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages? The <hi>Magistrate</hi> is the <hi>Civil Parent:</hi> and as God has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the <hi>Sword</hi> to him to cut off intolerable Miscreants, so has he given him a <hi>Rod</hi> to chastize Offenders in
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:41862:45"/> lesser Matters: and to him methinks we may as well apply the words of <hi>Solomon,</hi> as to the Natural Parent (Prov. 23. 14.) <hi>Thou shalt beat him with the Rod, and shalt deliver his Soul from Hell.</hi> Which if duly considered, would serve to quicken <hi>Magistrates</hi> in this glorious Work of saving the Souls of Men from <hi>eternal Torments</hi> (which would bring a great share of their Glory into their own Bosoms.) And it would also tend to allay the passio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Resentments of such as fall under the Correction of the <hi>Magistrates Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline,</hi> if they did but foresee the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valuable kindness of stopping their way (tho with Thorns) to prevent their running into the <hi>Infernal Pit.</hi> O that Men had Faith to make a due Estimate of these certain and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary Consequences of things! which a few Moments will exemplify upon every Soul of us in <hi>Eternal Bliss or Torment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IT was the deep sense of these great Things, which first engaged the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:41862:45"/> Hearts and Hands of those few Pious <hi>Gentlemen</hi> in this most Noble Work, who do not now (blessed be God) act alone in it. Several other <hi>Gentlemen</hi> and eminent <hi>Citizens</hi> are now incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated with them; and they meet frequently to superintend, direct, and pursue <hi>this best of Works</hi> (as one of our Pious <hi>Bishops</hi> calls it) consulting the best and most advisable Methods to carry it on, spending a great deal of time weekly, and sometimes daily in it, and furthering it by very large and honourable Contributions. And by these means many thousands of vicious and profane Persons have been brought to just Punishment; to which the late excellent Law against <hi>profane Swearing</hi> and <hi>Cursing</hi> has been very serviceable: and were it but enlarged in a Line or two, to make the Work of <hi>Information</hi> easier, it would soon banish the Hellish senseless Sin of <hi>Blasphemy</hi> out of this Nation; as also out of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> where it is likewise made a Law, and is very
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:41862:46"/> vigorously put in Execution: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which a <hi>Person of Quality</hi> writes thus from <hi>Dublin,</hi> in a Letter to his Friend in <hi>London,</hi> Octob. 28. 1697.</p>
            <p>
               <q>THE <hi>Reformation</hi> goes on in this <hi>City</hi> very vigorously: When we were presented with a <hi>thousand Warrants</hi> against profane Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, by a Gentleman from <hi>London,</hi> it was thought we should never have needed more: but those have all been put in Execution, and we are now upon printing a <hi>third thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand</hi> of them more. The last <hi>Lord's Day,</hi> I believe there were eight or nine Pounds levied in <hi>Ale-Houses;</hi> and above a Hundred <hi>Bakers</hi> have paid within this last Quarter for profaning the <hi>Lord's Day,</hi> in the Business of their Trade, besides <hi>Taylors, Drovers,</hi> and others; and <hi>Bawdy-Houses</hi> and <hi>Whores</hi> are hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed down with a high Hand. <hi>Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel</hi> is filled with them, and this without any great Assistance from
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:41862:46"/> the <hi>Magistracy.</hi> Some Persons of our <hi>Societies</hi> being put upon the <hi>Grand-Jury</hi> for the City, do it ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually: ten or twelve lewd Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men have been taken up in a Night, in the Houses as well as Streets; and this twice or thrice a Week. But I must add however, that this <hi>Reformation</hi> in every part of it, is beholden to our <hi>Recorder,</hi> who shews more Zeal and Application to it, than ever any <hi>Magistrate</hi> in <hi>London</hi> or <hi>Middlesex</hi> has done since I have been acquainted with these Matters.</q>
            </p>
            <p>THERE is also a <hi>Society</hi> of this kind in <hi>Drogheda,</hi> in <hi>Manouth,</hi> and in <hi>Kilkenny:</hi> and several <hi>Divines</hi> are endeavouring to plant them in otlier parts of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Ireland.</hi> But I return nearer home.</p>
            <p>TO awaken a just sense of the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity of <hi>Reformation</hi> of Manners in the City of <hi>London,</hi> there are four Sermons in the Year preached on this weighty Subject at <hi>Bow-Church</hi> in
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:41862:47"/>
               <hi>Cheapside;</hi> namely, on every Monday next following the four usual <hi>Quarter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>days,</hi> about Eleven in the Morning: And the like is done by <hi>Dissenters</hi> on four other Days.</p>
            <p>AND by the Blessing of Almighty God upon these Endeavours, a very considerable sense of <hi>Religion</hi> has been revived in many of this <hi>Nation,</hi> and a very conspicuous Check given to <hi>Debauchery.</hi> Insomuch that the general <hi>Odium,</hi> and the threatning Dangers of informing against Vice and Profaneness are almost extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guisht, and the blessed Work of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> set into such an excellent and successful Method, that the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward part of it would soon be effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, would but some few in every Street or Parish, who are of Place and Power, pull their Hands out of their Bosoms to engage in this <hi>honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and necessary Work;</hi> or would o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who are of Ability, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute as it becomes them, towards the Expence of it. For the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:41862:47"/> of lewd People, (as was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore observed) and the prosecution of them in the course of our Law is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry chargable; insomuch, that near a <hi>thousand Pounds</hi> have been expend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this Work by one of these <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties</hi> alone, within the space of the last four Years: As it may be proved by <hi>their Book of Accounts,</hi> to any one that desires it for any good End.</p>
            <p>AND that none may be discoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged on the account of the general O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver flowing of Vice, and the dispro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable fewness of Hands engag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to put a stop to it; let it but be considered, that the chief part of this Opposition to <hi>Publick Immorality,</hi> has been occasioned by the meeting of four or five private Persons together; who duly considering and bewailing the Height and Extent of the Sins of this Nation, came to a Resolution of doing their utmost to oppose it, in the due course of our Laws. An At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt which, methinks, seemed as Generous and Heroick, as that of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathan
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:41862:48"/> and his Armour-bearer,</hi> who being inspirited by God, resolved to attack a whole Army of <hi>Philistins</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>campt on a vast Hill: But the <hi>Lord of Hosts</hi> who led them on in this noble Enterprize, did successfully car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry them thorow it, to the utter Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfiture of those numerous Enemies of God. And since we may without rashness conclude, that this Effort a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst publick Sins has the same <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal</hi> with that of <hi>Jonathan,</hi> we hope it may at last attain the same <hi>End,</hi> tho this Attempt against numerous and heightned Enormities has as great Disadvantages as that, in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Estimate.</p>
            <p>O! what a Field of Honour lies here, before all Persons among us! In which <hi>Magistrates</hi> and <hi>Ministers</hi> are more especially concerned to be <hi>Lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> who are by their Offices designed to direct the Consciences, and regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the Conversations of Men. I beseech the Almighty and All-good God to inspirit and determine them
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:41862:48"/> effectually to this Work, to which he loudly calls them, a Work absolutely necessary, not only to our Prosperity, but Subsistence; and for want of which we are almost undone.</p>
            <p>AND in truth, the Glory of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, and the Support of our Church and State, are so manifestly concerned herein; that I cannot see how the <hi>Ministers of Justice,</hi> or of <hi>Divine Service,</hi> will be able to answer the unchristian Neglect of it, before the Lord Jesus Christ (the Judg of All) before <hi>whose Judgment-Seat we must all appear,</hi> and that very speedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Where two <hi>Armies</hi> are engaged in a bloody and uncertain Battel, how will those <hi>Regiments</hi> answer it to their <hi>Prince,</hi> who stood by and idly lookt on, without striking one hearty stroke in his Cause, to whom they vowed a <hi>Military Faithfulness</hi> to their Death? But above the rest, how will the <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers</hi> of those dastardly Troops an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer it to their <hi>Sovereign,</hi> who dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a little Danger and Hardship in
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:41862:49"/> his Service, more than his <hi>Royal Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasure?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AH Sirs! if we are now backward to contribute our utmost Endeavours in our several Stations towards the suppressing those impudent and scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Vices, whereby <hi>our God and his Holy Religion</hi> are so outragiously blasphemed: If we prefer carnal Ease, the Favour of Men, or any worldly Interest, before the Honour of our God, and the Propagation of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: What insupportable Shame, Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and Regret will at last seize us, and for ever torment us! And therefore I again beseech the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> to excite and fix in us all (even in <hi>Magistrates, Ministers,</hi> and all Ranks of <hi>People</hi>) a vigorous and effectual Zeal for his Holy Name and Will; and a just Concern for the languishing Repute of the <hi>Christian Name,</hi> and of the <hi>Reformed Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND as for all those various <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees</hi> of Men who have already set their Hands to this excellent Work,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:41862:49"/> may they never slacken their Hands, or pull them back. Let me entreat them to act in it with a Zeal, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancy and Purity of Intention, suta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to so Divine an Employment as that they engage in, to so great and good a Master as they serve, and to that infinite Reward which they may expect. Be not such Enemies to your selves, as to be <hi>weary of well-doing,</hi> since in a short <hi>time you will reap, if you faint not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O Christians! Look unto Jesus, who not only <hi>underwent the Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of Sinners,</hi> but <hi>endured the Cross,</hi> and <hi>despised the Shame, for the Glory which was set before him.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that as a <hi>Curse</hi> is threatned to such as <hi>do the Work of the Lord negligently:</hi> So a <hi>Crown</hi> is prepared for those <hi>who are faithful unto Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE Time of our Warfare is but short, and the Difficulty of it will be much sweetened by the <hi>promised Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter,</hi> and the Reward of well-doing will be of infinite Value, and eternal
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:41862:50"/> Duration. And as no Work in the World will be more commended of our Supreme Judg at last, than this of Reformation; since he himself <hi>sits as a Refiner's Fire, and as Fullers Soap,</hi> to purify and cleanse his People from their Sins; and since he will e're long consume that Reprobate <hi>Silver,</hi> which is not effectually refined by those means of <hi>Purification</hi> which he hath ordained: On all these accounts, I say, we have no Concern upon Earth so great, as to acquit our selves well in this our Spiritual Calling, not <hi>being slothful, but diligent Followers of them, who through Faith and Patience inherit the Promises.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND here I cannot but call upon our <hi>Dissenting Brethren,</hi> that as they have manifested a Christian Spirit in assisting us to suppress Vice, they would do no less in endeavouring to discountenance Strife, and to restore Unity. And let me entreat them, even by the Bowels of our common <hi>Lord and Saviour,</hi> that they studi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:41862:50"/> endeavour to dispose their Young Ones to follow after things which make for <hi>Peace, Ʋnity and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> (the desire of which seems deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imprest on the Spirits of <hi>our Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Young Men</hi>) that the Church of God may enjoy more peaceable and flourishing Days in the next Age, than it has in this.</p>
            <p>THE making of our Peace with God by effectual <hi>Reformation,</hi> and of <hi>Ʋnion</hi> among our selves by mutual Charity and Condescension, are the happiest Works that any Person can apply himself to on Earth. The Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction and peaceable Fruits of it here would be exceeding great, and the Reward of it hereafter inexpressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>NOW these <hi>Societies</hi> aforementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, seem in a great measure fitted to carry on both these great Designs; if at least there be any hope of such inestimable Blessings, left to such a profligate People as we are: For they have been instrumental to bring seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:41862:51"/>
               <hi>Quakers and Enthusiastick People</hi> to Baptism, and to a sober Mind; and of the Conversion of many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane Persons; and of bringing others to legal Punishment, who appeared otherwise incorrigible.</p>
            <p>AND many of our <hi>Ministers</hi> have sound by Experience, (as they have assured me) that the planting of one of these <hi>Societies</hi> in their <hi>Parish,</hi> has been a means of enlarging their <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations</hi> and <hi>Communions</hi> to a very great Increase; and not only so, but of introducing a more devout De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment in all <hi>Publick Ordinances.</hi> So that it is greatly to be wisht, that every <hi>Parochial Minister</hi> would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to erect a <hi>Society</hi> of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in his Parish, which he might do, if he could but find two or three Young Men, or House-keepers in it, of pious Inclinations, and a sober Life, (and if such a number as this cannot be found in any place, it is worse than <hi>Sodom</hi>) and He may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin a <hi>Society</hi> with these (as many of
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:41862:51"/> those which are now numerous, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan at first) till more be added to them <hi>by the Grace of God.</hi> A thing of this Nature heartily undertaken for the Glory of God, and attended with Prayer, Diligence and Patience, could hardly miscarry. And a good Minister would find his Work happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly furthered by such a <hi>Pious Nursery</hi> of Youth; and the poor Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood not a little comforted by their <hi>Charity:</hi> Yea, the very Money which is by the Law forfeited to the Poor, by Swearing, Drunkenness, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faning the Lord's Day, would be a seasonable Relief to the Poor in these hard times; for by these Penalties the Sum of 55 <hi>Pounds</hi> was lately raised in one Parish of this City within the space of one Year.</p>
            <p>AND tho this may well be num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred amongst their <hi>Charities</hi> to the Poor, especially since the late Law a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst profane Swearing has made the Forseitures to the Poor arise ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry high to some who will not forbear
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:41862:52"/> it even after the <hi>second Conviction:</hi> Yet their own Personal Alms to proper Objects of Charity, are very consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable. Their Contributions to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Excellent Design of erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Libraries</hi> in our <hi>Foreign Plantati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> is computed to amount to one hundred Pounds and upwards: And what they have expended in freeing of <hi>Prisoners,</hi> and relieving poor <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies,</hi> is not inconsiderable.</p>
            <p>AND besides, their manner of dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bursing their <hi>Bounty</hi> to sick and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tressed People, is such as renders it a double Benefit. For they usually send their Alms by the hands of two or more of their most serious Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, who make a personal enquiry into their Necessities, and usually in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce some seasonable Discourse su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to the Affliction of the <hi>Person</hi> or <hi>Family</hi> which they relieve; which many times proves the better <hi>Charity</hi> of the two. For the poor afflicted Persons being partly awakened by the <hi>Rod</hi> of God upon them; and being
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:41862:52"/> surprized by such a <hi>Visit</hi> and <hi>Bounty</hi> from Persons unknown to them, and not a little pleased to hear such sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voury Speeches drop from the Lips of <hi>Young Persons:</hi> All these things together have sometimes been happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly instrumental in propagating a Sense of <hi>Religion</hi> in some Persons who never before felt any thing of it; and of exciting it where it had before taken place. So that I have some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times had greater Thanks from some who (upon my Recommendation) have enjoy'd these Spiritual Expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions of their <hi>Charity, Compassion,</hi> and <hi>Consolation,</hi> than for their <hi>other Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> tho they have confest themselves almost ravisht in the consideration of both.</p>
            <p>IT has sometimes pleased God to reduce some of their own Members by Sickness, or other means, to a low Condition; and then they have duly call'd to mind the <hi>Apostolick Rule</hi> of <hi>shewing Piety at Home;</hi> they have af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded them sutable Supplies when
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:41862:53"/> living, and buried them decently when dead. And as they have found them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves greatly affected by <hi>Funeral Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> so they usually procure one at the <hi>Funeral</hi> of any of their <hi>Society;</hi> as considering that no <hi>Sermon</hi> is like to come with such Power upon Mens Souls, as that which is enforc'd by a moving Object of Mortality, to alarm the very Senses of Men, and to give a mortifying blow to all Carnality: So that tho this their Charity begins at Home, it does not end there.</p>
            <p>IT was an Act of great good Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and savoured no less of a <hi>Spirit</hi> becoming our <hi>Merciful Religion,</hi> which some of them express'd to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a poor <hi>Widow</hi> upon her Death-Bed, whom they found in extream Trouble, for fear lest her two young Children should be cast upon the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of her Relations, who were <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists,</hi> and by that means be brought up in their Errors; it being in the Reign of <hi>K. James</hi> II.</p>
            <pb n="105" facs="tcp:41862:53"/>
            <p>NOW to ease her distressed Spirit, some of these <hi>Young Men</hi> undertook to take care both to maintain and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducate these for lorn <hi>Orphans;</hi> giving the poor expiring Widow their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise so to do: And this greatly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to her quiet and comfortable Death, for she had lived a very good Life. And they fully discharged their Trust: They took care that the two Children (the one being five Years of Age, the other six) were maintain'd and instructed till they were fit to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Apprentices; and then got them good Places, by which they are put into a Capacity of living very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably.</p>
            <p>I was once present at one of their <hi>Conferences,</hi> when a very poor Man came with most earnest Affection to return them Thanks for what they had done, both for his Body and Soul. It seems he was a perfect Stranger to them all, and to every other Person in the Place where God cast him down by a sharp and long Sickness, in which
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:41862:54"/> (as he said) his Body and Soul had like to have perish'd together. He had lived a very ill Life, and been much disused to the <hi>Ordinances</hi> of God, by reason of his Sea-faring Life: and being now come on shore sick, and being above a hundred Miles from his Abode and Acquaintance, he fell into great Want. Upon which, some of this <hi>Society</hi> perceiving his Distress, recommended him to the rest; and they readily allowed him a weekly Pension for eight Weeks together, till he was recovered. And one of the <hi>Society</hi> being a <hi>Chirurgeon,</hi> carefully dressed a very grievous Sore which he had, and by God's Blessing, restored it to perfect Soundness. Others of them went to him and read good Books by his Bed, which tended to the improvement of God's Visitation upon him: They also fetch'd the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister</hi> of the Place to him, who visited him often, and prayed by him, and got a Collection from some charitable Neighbours for him. And upon the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:41862:54"/> whole, he recovered, and seem'd to be a reformed Man, and came then to render his Praises to God, and Thanks to his Christian Friends, for that which had been done for him.</p>
            <p>I mention but one of Multitudes of such Instances, which seem to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrate such <hi>Compassion</hi> and <hi>Conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scension</hi> of Spirit as is essential to a <hi>Christian,</hi> and which was the <hi>Beauty and Glory</hi> of <hi>Primitive Christianity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BEFORE I conclude, it may be expected that I give some Description of the <hi>Weekly Conferences,</hi> and <hi>joint De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions</hi> of our <hi>Religious Societies:</hi> But I need not insist on this, since the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of both is hereto annexed, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for their Use, and partly to prevent Misrepresentation by false Reports. So that I shall only add, That as they use very affecting Presaces before they pray to God, or praise his Great and Holy Name, to raise and fix their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Devotion; so they always use a very reverend outward Deportment in the Worship of God, that their
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:41862:55"/> Body may not seem to mock or dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>approve of that which their Soul is doing: Which is surely agreeable to all <hi>sober Reason,</hi> and <hi>sound Religion.</hi> Our <hi>Creator, Redeemer,</hi> and <hi>Sanctifier,</hi> ought to be owned, worshiped, and glorified with those Bodies (as well as those Souls) which his <hi>Almighty Power, Wisdom</hi> and <hi>Goodness,</hi> hath created, redeemed, doth sanctify, and will glorify. So that in Prayer, they all kneel, according to the direction of the Spirit of God, <hi>Psal.</hi> 95. 6. And according to our Blessed Saviour's Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample; <hi>Luke 22. 41. He kneeled down and prayed.</hi> And in <hi>singing of Psalms,</hi> or any other <hi>solemn Doxology,</hi> they stand up; which is surely the fittest Posture for this exalted part of God's Worship. And if I may speak my own Experiences, I think we shall find our Souls greatly raised by our Bodily Reverence. Tho it be still al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, That the spiritual Reverence of the Soul is vastly the chiefest, and that in all bodily Weakness, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:41862:55"/> necessary Impediments, <hi>God will have Mercy, and not Sacrifice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>MANY of them meet together at each others Houses also in the Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of many <hi>Feasts of the Church</hi> and <hi>Holy Days;</hi> where they discourse se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously on the Subject-matter of the Day; by which they find themselves much informed in many essential Parts of the <hi>Christian Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THESE their Holy Purposes have for a considerable time been cherish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and improved by some of our Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Bishops,</hi> who have often preach'd to them on these Occasions: And in particular, one of them has for many Years allowed them the use of his Church, and been present at the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons which they procured, and has also written a most excellent <hi>Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of these beginnings of <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> And another of them (who has sometime given a most illustrious Instance of his Care in cultivating Youth, by training up <hi>Young Scholars</hi> for the Ministry, not only at his own
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:41862:56"/> Expence, but by his personal Instructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them) hath published to the World the great Delight with which our late <hi>Pious Queen</hi> received the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of this hopeful Method of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming of Youth by these <hi>Societies,</hi> and with what Concern she often in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired after it. His words are these: <hi>She did hearken carefully after every thing that seemed to give some Hope, that the next Generation should be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than the present, with a particular Attention: She heard of a Spirit of Devotion and Piety that was spreading it self among the Youth of this great City, with a true Satisfaction: She en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired often and much about it, and was glad to hear it went on and prevailed,</hi> Essay, <hi>pag.</hi> 118.</p>
            <p>In this desired <hi>Reformation of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> our <hi>Right Reverend Diocesan</hi> (the Lord Bishop of <hi>London</hi>) has like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise appeared several times with great Honour. His <hi>Lordship</hi>'s Letter to his <hi>Clergy</hi> about eight Years since, (pursuant to the Scope of his <hi>Majesty's
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:41862:56"/> Proclamation and special Orders</hi> relat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this Affair) was very service<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to this Purpose. In which his <hi>Lordship</hi> required all the <hi>Ministers</hi> of his <hi>Diocess</hi> (upon certain <hi>Lord's Days</hi> therein prefixt) to read the several <hi>Acts of Parliament</hi> against Vice and Profaneness, in the Audience of their respective Congregations; and at the same time to bend the Scope of their <hi>Sermons</hi> against the Sins thereby con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, that the Force and Terror of the Laws of God and Men might at once make the utmost Impression in the Consciences of their Hearers, in order to reform the <hi>notorious Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressions</hi> of both.</p>
            <p>AND forasmuch as this <hi>Injunction</hi> was mistaken by some, as if it reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no further than the Year in which it was dated; his <hi>Lordship</hi> was pleas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his last Visitation of the <hi>Clergy of Middlesex,</hi> to remind them of the continuance of his Injunction in that Matter requiring them to observe it according to the <hi>Order</hi> before sent them.</p>
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:41862:57"/>
            <p> YEA, further yet, that nothing may be wanting to awaken such a vigilant and consciencious Care in the discharge of this Great Duty, as is necessary to the Character of a <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster of the Lord Jesus Christ,</hi> and to express our Thankfulness to <hi>Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God</hi> for the marvelous Mercies which he has vouchsafed to this <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> his <hi>Lordship</hi> has newly directed another Letter to his <hi>Clergy,</hi> wherein he complains of the Nonobservance of his <hi>Majesty</hi>'s Injunctions of <hi>Febr.</hi> 13. 1689/90. (which related to their reading of the <hi>Laws</hi> of the Land a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Vice</hi> and <hi>Impiety</hi>) and takes occasion (from the Assurance which his <hi>Majesty</hi> has given to the Publick, in his late Speech to both Houses of <hi>Parliament,</hi> That <hi>he will make it one of his chief Cares to suppress Profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and-Immorality</hi>) to represent to his Clergy, <hi>what a shameful Reproach it would be to them, (a great part of whose Business it ought to be, continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to-watch against such Sins) to be
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:41862:57"/> found tardy in those Opportunities which the Laws have given them to warn Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of their wicked Courses.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND it is greatly hoped, That no <hi>Minister</hi> hereby admonished, will be so unmindful of the Sacred Vows of <hi>Christianity,</hi> and the Special Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his Holy <hi>Function,</hi> or so negligent of the Interests of his <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Master,</hi> and of the <hi>Souls</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to his Charge; as to disregard so solemn and seasonable an Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition.</p>
            <p>SEVERAL other of our <hi>Bishops</hi> have also of late sent very pious <hi>Letters</hi> to the <hi>Clergy</hi> under their <hi>Episcopal Care,</hi> earnestly pressing their most studious Concern to propagate sincere Piety in their several <hi>Parishes,</hi> by their Holy Doctrine and Examples.</p>
            <p>AND truly, since there is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently so much Goodness in these <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties</hi> and <hi>Designs,</hi> as to give us Hope <hi>they are of God;</hi> we have thence a so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid ground to hope <hi>that they will not come to nought.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="114" facs="tcp:41862:58"/>
            <p>IN this Hope I have often been en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, when I have observed with what Delight and Industry they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secute their Holy Purposes. I have known some of them (who have been at their own Liberty) come out of the midst of the <hi>City</hi> (after their Shops have been shut) three or four Miles to the outmost Parts of the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs,</hi> to give Instruction and Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to a new-planted <hi>Society;</hi> returning again a considerable time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Night, in all the Inconveniencies of the Darkness and uncertain Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with the chearing Thought of having been well imployed.</p>
            <p>I must also further note, to the Praise and Glory of <hi>Almighty God,</hi> by what remarkable <hi>Providences</hi> it hath pleased him to further this Divine Work: For the Conversions of some of those <hi>Young Men</hi> who have been very instrumental in this Affair, have been very wonderful.</p>
            <p>ONE of them had such an affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Dream of the <hi>Day of Judgment,</hi>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:41862:58"/> that he forthwith became a very zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Servant of God; and was so sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible of the importance of securing Peace with God, and redeeming Time, that for several Years together he spent the greatest part of the Night in Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Pious Exercises, as his Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellow informs me. He also begged leave of his Master to retire a little while to his <hi>Devotions</hi> at Noon, and to have Liberty to partake of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of some publick <hi>Sermons</hi> and <hi>Prayers,</hi> promising to give him Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for it when he came out of his Time; which accordingly he did, tho it does not speak the Piety or <hi>Charity</hi> of his Master, who required it of him.</p>
            <p>ANOTHER of them (tho in perfect Health) could not rest in his Bed for several Nights together, which at last brought him upon his Knees to ask it of God, with some Sorrow for his Sins, (for he had lived a very ill Life) and he found such ease to his Mind thereby, that it presently conduced to his bodily Rest; which led him to
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:41862:59"/> the further Exercise of it, especially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he went to Bed. And then taking some Delight in the Duty, he fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented the <hi>Evening Prayers</hi> set up at eight of the Clock by these <hi>Societies;</hi> where he observed the affectionate Devotions of these <hi>associated Young Men;</hi> and after Prayers, made his Condition known to some of them, who mightily assisted him in the Ways of God, till he became a fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Communicant.</p>
            <p>ANOTHER of them was told by an idle prating Woman, that she was perswaded he would not live long, which she grounded upon a most im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent Observation, not worthy to be mentioned. But this jesting Talk awakened him in good earnest to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare to die; So <hi>powerful is a trivial Means in the Hands of the Almighty God:</hi> Whereupon he spent the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est part of the following Night in Prayer, with earnest <hi>Vows</hi> and <hi>Tears;</hi> And he has lived a very devout and exemplary Life ever since, which is about nine Years.</p>
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:41862:59"/>
            <p>MANY others have, in my hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, praised God that ever they were acquainted with these <hi>Christian Asso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciates:</hi> And have owned, that their Knowledg of God, and Conversion to him, were occasioned thereby; yea, I never yet met with one Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of any of these <hi>Societies,</hi> who did not greatly praise God for the Benefit they reap from them.</p>
            <p>AND since the time that the Use<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulness of these <hi>Societies</hi> has been vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible to the World, their Zeal hath provoked some of their <hi>Dissenting Brethren</hi> to join with them occasional<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and to set up the like among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves. And who knows but that this <hi>Essential Ʋnion</hi> of theirs in the Love of God and Goodness, may at last draw them to center in the same <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion;</hi> and so bring a most inesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable Blessing to this <hi>bleeding Church and State?</hi> Than which no Blessing upon Earth can be imagined greater. For, it would mightily strengthen the languishing Interest of <hi>Protestancy;</hi>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:41862:60"/> and envigorate the Power of our <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Religion;</hi> and be the best and surest Foundation of a vigorous and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Reformation.</hi> And this, in a time when both <hi>Ʋnion</hi> and <hi>Reformation</hi> are almost despair'd of. And if once the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> of God vouchsafes us these his Heavenly Fruits of <hi>Ʋnity</hi> and <hi>Purity, England</hi> will indeed be <hi>the Glory of all Nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IN fine, we have here many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of young, sober, and active Men, freely and solemnly engaging themselves to live strictly as it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh our <hi>Holy Religion,</hi> (the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of which is at this Day deplora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly sunk) and humbly offering their utmost Service to our <hi>Magistrates</hi> and <hi>Ministers,</hi> in order to suppress the publick Practice of those <hi>scandalous and insolent Sins</hi> which endanger both our <hi>Church and State.</hi> And there seems to be a zealous and generous Spirit in them animating them to this <hi>noble Enterprize:</hi> And they are put into an excellent Method to carry it
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:41862:60"/> on in all the parts of the City, of which they have already given suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient proof. And truly, if these Means of <hi>Reformation</hi> be not accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it will be difficult to find out any other that are so like to effect it, or to <hi>better the next Generation, in which all our Hope of Prosperity on Earth seems to lie.</hi> So then, if it shall please Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons in <hi>Place and Power</hi> to improve this <hi>Talent</hi> laid before them, by strengthning those Hands which are heartily stretcht forth against Profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, but need their Assistance to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect it: What eminent Service may be done <hi>for God and these Kingdoms</hi> in this Season? But if this Design be mockt and brow-beaten, (as many things proposed for the <hi>Publick Good,</hi> and this in particular hath been) and if some vain People give it a <hi>Nick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name,</hi> and term it an <hi>imprudent or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seasonable Zeal,</hi> or the like, and then the rest decry and discourage it, or at least are a shamed to own it, or appear for it; I am perswaded, That notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:41862:61"/> the common Cry of <hi>Peace, Peace,</hi> it will be hard to assign good Proof, <hi>that we are not near to Desolation.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> A Specimen of the <hi>Orders</hi> of the <hi>Societies</hi> before mentioned.</head>
            <div n="1" type="order">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>THAT the sole <hi>Design</hi> of this <hi>Society</hi> being to <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 15.</note> promote real Holiness of Heart and Life: It is absolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary that the Persons who enter into it, do seriously re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solve to apply themselves in <note place="margin">Josh. 24. 15.</note> good earnest to all means pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to <hi>make them wise unto Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 15.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="order">
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:41862:61"/>
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>THAT in order to their being of <hi>one Heart and one</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 15. 5, 6. Phil. 2. 2.</note>
                  <hi>Mind</hi> in this Design, every Member of this <hi>Society</hi> shall own and manifest himself to be of the <hi>Church of England,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 13.</note> and frequent the <hi>Liturgy,</hi> and other publick Holy Exercises of the same. And that they be careful withal to express due Christian <hi>Charity, Candor</hi> and <hi>Moderation</hi> towards all <note place="margin">Eph. 4. 2. Rom. 12. 18.</note> such Dissenters as are of good Conversation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="order">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>THAT the Members of this <hi>Society</hi> shall meet together one Evening in the Week at a <note place="margin">1 Thess. 5. 14. Rom. 14. 19.</note> convenient Place, in order to encourage each other in <hi>prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Holiness,</hi> by discoursing on Spiritual Subjects, and read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God's Holy Word; and to pray to <hi>Almighty God,</hi> and <note place="margin">Psal. 34. 3.</note> praise his Name together.</p>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:41862:62"/>
               <p>AND to this Assembly any serious Person may be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, upon Request.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="order">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <p>THAT at such <hi>Meetings,</hi> there be no hot Disputes about Controversial Points, State-Affairs, or the Concerns of Trade and worldly Things: <note place="margin">Rom. 15. 6.</note> But that the whole Bent of the Discourse be to <hi>glorify God, and edify one another in Love.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 4. 16.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="order">
               <head>V.</head>
               <p>THAT it be left to every Person's Discretion to contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute at every <hi>Weekly Meeting,</hi> what he thinks fit towards a <hi>Publick Stock</hi> for Pious and <note place="margin">1 Cor. 16. 2.</note> Charitable Uses: And the Money thus collected shall be kept by the two <hi>Stewards</hi> of the <hi>Society,</hi> (who shall be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen by majority of Voices once a Year or oftner) to be disposed of by the Consent
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:41862:62"/> of the major part of the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety,</hi> for the Uses above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned. And the said <hi>Stewards</hi> shall keep a faithful <hi>Register</hi> of what is thus col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected and distributed, to be perused by any Member of the <hi>Society,</hi> at his Request.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="order">
               <head>VI.</head>
               <p>THAT any respective Member may recommend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Object of Charity to the <hi>Stewards,</hi> who shall (with the Consent of the rest) give out of the <hi>Common Stock,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as the Occasion requires. And in a Case of extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Necessity, every particular Person shall be desired to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute further, as they shall think fit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="order">
               <head>VII.</head>
               <p>THAT every one that ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sents himself four Meetings together, (without giving a satisfactory Account to the
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:41862:63"/>
                  <hi>Stewards)</hi> shall be lookt upon as disaffected to the <hi>Society.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="order">
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <p>THAT none shall be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into this <hi>Society,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out giving due notice thereof to the <hi>Stewards,</hi> who shall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint the whole <hi>Society</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. And after due enquiry into their Religious <hi>Purposes,</hi> and <hi>manner of Life,</hi> the Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards may <hi>admit</hi> them to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe their Names, if the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor part of the Society allows of it, and not otherwise. And with the like joint Consent, they may <hi>exclude</hi> any Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber proved guilty of any Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>behaviour after due Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, unless he gives suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Testimony of his Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Amendment, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the whole <hi>Society.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="order">
               <head>IX.</head>
               <p>IT is hereby recommended to every Person concerned in
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:41862:63"/> this <hi>Society,</hi> to consider the many Inconveniencies, (and many times Sins) which at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend <hi>Ale-House-Games,</hi> and <note place="margin">Gal. 5. 13.</note> wholly decline them. And to shun all unnecessary resort to such Houses and Taverns, <note place="margin">1 Thess. 5. 22.</note> and wholly to avoid lewd <hi>Play-Houses.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="order">
               <head>X.</head>
               <p>THAT the respective Members of this <hi>Society,</hi> shall heartily endeavour, through God's Grace;</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. TO be <hi>just</hi> in all their <note place="margin">1 Thess. 4. 6.</note> Dealings, even to an exempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Strictness.</item>
                  <item>2. TO <hi>pray</hi> many times e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very <note place="margin">1 Thess. 5. 17.</note> Day: Remembring our continual dependence upon God, both for Spiritual and Temporal Things.</item>
                  <item>3. To partake of the <hi>Lord's</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 26. Luke 22. 19.</note>
                     <hi>Supper</hi> at least once a Month, if not prevented by a reasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Impediment.</item>
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:41862:64"/>
                  <item>4. TO practise the <hi>profound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Meekness and Humility.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 11. 29.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. TO watch against <hi>cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suring</hi> others. <note place="margin">Mat. 7. 1.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>6. TO accustom themselves to <hi>holy Thoughts</hi> in all places. <note place="margin">Psal. 139. 23.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>7. TO be helpful one to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. <note place="margin">1 Cor. 12. 25.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>8. To exercise Tenderness, <note place="margin">Tit. 3. 2.</note> Patience, and Compassion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all Men.</item>
                  <item>9. TO make Reflections on themselves when they read the <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10. 11.</note>
                     <hi>Holy Bible,</hi> or other good <hi>Books,</hi> and when they hear Sermons.</item>
                  <item>10. TO shun all foreseen <hi>Occasions</hi> of <hi>Evil:</hi> As evil Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, known Temptations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Thess. 5. 22.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>11. TO think often on the different Estates of the <hi>Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied</hi> and the <hi>Damned</hi> in the <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable Eternity,</hi> to which we are hastening. <note place="margin">Luke 16. 25.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>12. TO <hi>examine</hi> themselves every Night, what <hi>Good</hi> or <note place="margin">2 Cor. 13. 5.</note>
                     <hi>Evil</hi> they have done in the Day past.</item>
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:41862:64"/>
                  <item>13. TO keep a <hi>private Fast</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 6. 16.</note> once a Month, (especially near their approach to the <hi>Lord's</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luke 5. 35.</note>
                     <hi>Table)</hi> if at their own disposal; or to fast from some Meals when they may conveniently.</item>
                  <item>14. TO mortify the Flesh <note place="margin">Gal. 5. 19, 24.</note> with its Affections and Lusts.</item>
                  <item>15. TO advance in <hi>heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3. 8.</note>
                     <hi>mindedness,</hi> and in all <hi>Grace.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>16. To shun <hi>Spiritual Pride,</hi> and the Effects of it, as Rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Anger, Peevishness, and Impatience of Contradiction, and the like.</item>
                  <item>17. TO pray for the <hi>whole</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Jam. 5. 16.</note>
                     <hi>Society</hi> in their private Prayers.</item>
                  <item>
                     <p>18. TO read pious Books <note place="margin">Joh. 5. 39.</note> often for their Edification, but especially the <hi>Holy Bible:</hi> And herein particularly,</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 5, 6, 7, Chap. <hi>Luke</hi> 15, 16, Chap. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12, 13, Chap. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5, 6, Chap. 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 5, Chap. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1, 2, 3, 21, 22, Chapters.</p>
                     <pb n="128" facs="tcp:41862:65"/>
                     <p>And in the <hi>Old Testament, Levit.</hi> 26, Chap. <hi>Deut.</hi> 28, Chap. <hi>Isa.</hi> 53, Chap. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36, Chap.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item>19. TO be continually mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of the great Obligation of this <hi>special Profession of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> and to walk so circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spectly, that none may be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended or discouraged from it by what they see in them; nor occasion given to any to speak reproachfully of it.</item>
                  <item>20. TO shun all manner of Affectation and Moroseness; and be of a civil and obliging Deportment to all Men.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="order">
               <head>XI.</head>
               <p>THAT they often consider (with an awful dread of God's Wrath) the sad <hi>Height</hi> to which the Sins of many are <note place="margin">Mal. 3. 16.</note> advanced in this our Nation; and the bleeding <hi>Divisions</hi> thereof in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State.</hi> And that every Member be <note place="margin">Judg. 5. 15.</note>
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:41862:65"/> ready to do, what upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sulting with each other shall be thought advisable, towards <note place="margin">Deut. 13. 8. Levit. 24. 11.</note> the punishment of <hi>publick Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneness,</hi> according to the good Laws of our Land, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to be put in Execution by the <hi>King</hi>'s and the late <hi>Queen</hi>'s special Order.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="order">
               <head>XII.</head>
               <p>THAT each Member shall <note place="margin">Deut. 6. 7. Josh. 24. 15.</note> encourage the <hi>Catechizing</hi> of young and ignorant People in their respective Families, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Stations and Abilities: And shall observe all manner of Religious <hi>Family-Duties.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="order">
               <head>XIII.</head>
               <p>THAT the major Part of the <hi>Society</hi> shall have Power to make a new <hi>Order</hi> to bind the whole when need requires; if it be approved by a pious and learned <hi>Minister</hi> of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> nominated by the whole <hi>Society.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="order">
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:41862:66"/>
               <head>XIV.</head>
               <p>THAT these <hi>Orders</hi> shall be read over at least four times in the Year by one of the <hi>Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards;</hi> And that with such de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation, that each Member may have time to examine himself by them, or to speak his Mind in any thing relating to them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="order">
               <head>XV.</head>
               <p>LASTLY, That ever Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of this <hi>Society</hi> shall (after mature deliberation, and due trial) subscribe his Name to these Orders; to express his <hi>Approbation</hi> of them, and his <hi>Resolution</hi> to endeavour to live up to them. In order to which, he shall constantly keep a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py of <hi>them by him.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>The End of the Orders.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <pb n="131" facs="tcp:41862:66"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> The Reason of this Publication of the Orders and Design of these So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties.</head>
            <p>HAVING found by discourse with several Persons (who have greatly rejoiced to hear of any <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Good</hi> set on foot) that they never before heard of these <hi>Societies;</hi> I could not but wonder that a thing of this Nature could so long remain secret.</p>
            <p>THEY have been erected in our <hi>Capital City</hi> above nineteen Years; They procure Sermons by way of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration for the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> or to engage a sutable Holiness of Life af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it, every <hi>Lord's Day</hi> about five in the Evening, in many of the largest Churches in the City: Their <hi>Charity</hi> is extended to deserving Objects in all the Parts of the <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Suburbs.</hi> And
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:41862:67"/> by their Procurement, <hi>Publick Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> are daily made in several Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, at such Hours as they can most conveniently be present at them. And by the means of their great Zeal and giving Informations, a Multitude of such as have no fear of God before their Eyes, have been punish'd for their <hi>Profaneness and Debauchery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>SO that it is to be admired, that their good Deeds and Designs could be so long unknown to so many. But truly this does very much recommend their <hi>Christian Modesty,</hi> it demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates that they do not affect to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish either their <hi>Alms</hi> or <hi>Devotion,</hi> after the vaunting manner of the <hi>Pharisees,</hi> with which our <hi>Blessed Saviour</hi> was so highly offended; but that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to manage their Holy Purposes in the most <hi>humble Silence</hi> and <hi>contrived Secrecy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I conceived therefore, that it might probably conduce to the enlargement of these useful <hi>Societies,</hi> and to engage the Prayers of good People in their
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:41862:67"/> behalf, to give some Publick Account of their <hi>Constitution, Design,</hi> and <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> all which have been approved by divers eminent Divines; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, by our late excellent Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, <hi>Arch-Bishop Tillotson,</hi> who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had examin'd their <hi>Orders,</hi> and the trifling Objections that were made against them by some Persons, declared it as his Opinion publickly, and upon several Occasions, That these <hi>Societies</hi> were a Support to our <hi>Church;</hi> and surely they will not be ashamed to appear in Publick, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever the <hi>Christian Religion</hi> does.</p>
            <p>AND tho there be some little vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations in the <hi>Orders</hi> of some of these <hi>Societies</hi> from others, yet the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of them is generally one and the same: In which I beseech the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit</hi> to establish every Soul en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged therein, and to incline others to be <hi>followers of them in that which is Good.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="134" facs="tcp:41862:68"/>
            <p>THAT we have absolute need of <hi>Reformation</hi> from the Highest to the Lowest, and that it highly concerns us to set about it with speed, are Truths so manifest, that I need not stand to prove them to any Person of serious and sober Thought. All such must of necessity conclude with me, <hi>That unless it be effected speedily, we are undone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND I think it will as little be questioned by sober Men, but that these <hi>Societies</hi> do very directly tend towards that desired Effect: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, since some <hi>Objections</hi> have been made against them, we will now take them into Consideration.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <pb n="135" facs="tcp:41862:68"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> The chief Objections which have been made against these Societies, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered and answered by some of their Members.</head>
            <p>I. WHEREAS it has been object<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That there is danger of <hi>Schism and Dissension</hi> by their weekly meeting, and conferring together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Religious Matters:</p>
            <p>THEY answer, 1. That they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conceive where this Danger lies; since no Persons do more professedly own the Holy Doctrine and Consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the <hi>Church of England</hi> than themselves, desiring always to be found in their Practice agreeable there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto: And that none do more sincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reverence and esteem the <hi>Publick
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:41862:69"/> Ministry,</hi> nor more constantly and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verently attend upon the <hi>Publick Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances:</hi> In the great Esteem of which (in subordination to the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, and their own and others Salvation) they have at their own Expence set up daily <hi>Publick Prayers</hi> in many Churches, (after due leave obtained) and have procured (thrô the Assistance of several Pious Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines) the Benefit of <hi>weekly Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> in many Churches, which they frequent in great Numbers.</p>
            <p>2. THAT some of their Members had by their Examples influenced se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>Dissenters</hi> to come to Church, and been a means of bringing several <hi>Anabaptists and Quakers</hi> to Baptism. That they had also been instrumental of preserving from <hi>Popery</hi> several un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steddy and wavering People, in the late Rage of that <hi>Spiritual Plague,</hi> and of reducing many licentious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons to Holiness of Life.</p>
            <p>3. THAT as all controversial Points are forbidden by their <hi>Orders</hi>
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:41862:69"/> to be medled with in their Conferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, (because they only design to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote practical Holiness by their as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembling together) so in their reading of those practical Portions of <hi>Holy Scripture</hi> to which their <hi>Orders</hi> direct them, they have recourse to Dr. <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi>'s Exposition, or some other Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor recommended by their Ministers.</p>
            <p>4. THAT it had in Fact been ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified for these twenty Years past, that but one Member of these <hi>Societies</hi> had (to the best of their knowledg) lest the Communion of the <hi>Church of England</hi> for any other; of which singular Defection some special Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons may be given.</p>
            <p>LASTLY, That leaving Matters of Fact, they did appeal to the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents of all good People; whether their reading of the Word of God, with the most Orthodox Expositors; their Praying and singing Psalms to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, with their Exhorting, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving, and encouraging one another in their Spiritual Warfare, have any
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:41862:70"/> tendency in Reason, and in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of things to make Schismaticks? Or rather, whether any <hi>Church of Christ</hi> will not most certainly be the more established and advanced by the conscientious and general Practice of such Holy Exercises?</p>
            <p>II. WHEREAS others have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, that ill and designing Men may get into these <hi>Societies</hi> (as <hi>Popish Emissaries have into some others</hi>) and quite pervert their Design, (how good soever in the first Institution) to the prejudice of the <hi>Church:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THEY answer, 1. That their <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> forbid the admittance of any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son into their <hi>Societies</hi> (as Members) who is not known to some of the rest, and who does not frequent the <hi>Publick Ordinances</hi> in that way of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistration which is by Law establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: Which is a Caution they use to prevent Differences and Disorder and effectually excludes such as are mentioned by the <hi>Objector.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="139" facs="tcp:41862:70"/>
            <p>2. THAT they are so manifestly studious to comply with the Rules of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and to yield a just <hi>Obedience to those that are set over them in the Lord;</hi> that they have been many times censured as guilty of rigid Severity, and Uncharitableness towards <hi>Dissenting Protestants;</hi> which they must likewise account an injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Treatment; Forasmuch as they endeavour to shun all extreams, being desirous to practise <hi>Christian Subjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> without prejudice to <hi>Christian Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>III. TO those who <hi>object,</hi> That by their Reproving and Admonish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing those they converse with; and by their visiting the Sick, and sometimes praying with them; they do invade and intrude upon the <hi>Ministers Office:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THEY reply, 1. That since they are commanded of God, <hi>in any wise to reprove their Brother, and not to suffer Sin upon him;</hi> And to <hi>exhort one another daily, lest any be hardened by the deceitfulness of Sin;</hi> They humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:41862:71"/> that their Christian <hi>Admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> and <hi>Reproofs</hi> can by no good Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son be censured as an intrusion upon the <hi>Ministerial Function.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. THAT since the Duty of <hi>visit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Sick, and administring to them,</hi> is one of the great things which will be enquired into by their <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Saviour</hi> at the last Judgment: And since all People are commanded <hi>to pray one for another;</hi> they cannot account it an invasion upon the <hi>Minister's Office,</hi> if at such time as the Minister cannot be present, they use an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved Form of Prayer sutable to the Condition of the Sick Person (which they humbly conceive any <hi>Christian Friend</hi> may and ought upon Request to do for another, who by Sickness is disabled from doing it himself) and in any case or manner but this, they do not practise it.</p>
            <p>IV. TO such as suggest, that there is Danger of <hi>Spiritual Pride</hi> in these Societies, by their making a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and special Profession of Religion
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:41862:71"/> and being thought <hi>more Holy than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers:</hi> They reply,</p>
            <p n="1">1. THAT they cannot think it warrantable to omit any part of <hi>Christian Duty</hi> for fear of <hi>Spiritual Pride, or seeming holier than others:</hi> Since then, for the same Reason they might omit the whole.</p>
            <p n="2">2. THAT it is indeed a due Sense of their own and others <hi>Infirmities</hi> which induces them to unite into <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties</hi> (since <hi>two are stronger than one,</hi> many than few), knowing that the Difficulties are very many, and very great, which they must encounter in their Passage towards <hi>Eternal Life:</hi> And that such is the Degeneracy, even <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f <hi>Christians</hi> in these latter days, that through the <hi>Profaneness</hi> of some, and <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>Lukewarmness and Cowardice</hi> of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hers, they should but seldom meet with such Conversation as is highly <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xpedient for the keeping up a due <hi>Warmth and Life</hi> in Spiritual Things; were it not for those frequent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>rences, and pious Exercises which
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:41862:72"/> are (with good Effect) set up by these <hi>Societies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>V. WHEREAS it is <hi>objected,</hi> That since a Church of <hi>Christ</hi> is a <hi>Society of Christian People;</hi> and that these So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties are erected in a <hi>Reformed Church.</hi> That this is a Society with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a Society, and a Refining upon a <hi>Reformed Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>TO this they humbly reply;</p>
            <p n="1">1. THAT they have not yet learnt, that the reading of <hi>God's Word,</hi> and conferring on the practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Points of <hi>Religion,</hi> in order to a more holy Conversation, hath at any time by good Men been thought pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial to the <hi>Church of Christ.</hi> On the contrary; Our best <hi>Divines</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend these things both from the Pulpit and the Press, as the best Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedients to support and adorn our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Church,</hi> and render it worthy of that <hi>Venerable Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. THAT they do not well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand what the Objector means by <hi>refining upon our Reformed Church</hi>
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:41862:72"/> If it be meant, that they pretend to reform her <hi>Doctrine,</hi> or quarrel with her <hi>Government;</hi> they utterly dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim any such practice. But if it be meant, that they desire to <hi>refine and reform</hi> themselves and others, so as to come nearer to her <hi>Purity of Doctrine</hi> in their practice, than some others do, who shelter their <hi>profane Lives</hi> under the pretence of her <hi>Holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion:</hi> They own this, and must adhere to it, not doubting but they shall have the Prayers of all good Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that they may so do.</p>
            <p>UPON the whole Matter there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, they conclude; That since their <hi>Societies</hi> are neither against the Word of God, nor the Laws of Man; but manifestly conducive to God's Glory, the Salvation of Men, and the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Interest of our <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> And since they have proved very beneficial to the Souls of the Members, and are agreeable to the Primitive Practice of the <hi>best Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and tend so directly to revive
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:41862:73"/> something of their Primitive Purity and Zeal for Religion; together with their Charity, and good Works: They humbly crave, That these <hi>Societies</hi> may be encouraged by their <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours in Church and State,</hi> sutably to the <hi>Spiritual and National</hi> Benefits which may be reapt from them.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> An Admonition to the Members of these Societies.</head>
            <p>HAVING thus far described and vindicated these <hi>Societies,</hi> which I verily think for the most part sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely <hi>Religious:</hi> I now turn me to the respective Members of them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seeching them, even for the Honour of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Goodness,</hi> that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port themselves so, that a sincere Lover of <hi>Religion</hi> may with Honour plead for them.</p>
            <pb n="145" facs="tcp:41862:73"/>
            <p>LET me earnestly entreat you, <hi>my most beloved Brethren,</hi> that ye walk worthy of your special Profession of <hi>Religion,</hi> and of your pious Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings, which are honourable in the sight of God, and Angels, and Men.</p>
            <p>IT will be expected from you, that ye shew your selves exemplary in all the practical Points of our Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Religion, such as <hi>Purity, Patience, Humility, Temperance, Charity, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly-mindness,</hi> and the like: because this is the very End of your <hi>Religious Associations.</hi> O! be not wanting to gain your <hi>main Point:</hi> For indeed, not only those who disrespect you, but even those that wish you best, will be apt to ask, <hi>What do ye more than others?</hi> Yea, as our <hi>Great Lord and Master</hi> has done more for you than for many others, he will (as a Righteous Judg) put that very Ques<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to you at the last Day, as we find it proceeding from his own Lips, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 47.</p>
            <pb n="146" facs="tcp:41862:74"/>
            <p>ALL the <hi>real Disciples</hi> of Christ do abundantly more for their Master than <hi>Publicans,</hi> and the unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Part of the World. They have <hi>much forgiven</hi> them by God, and they <hi>love him much.</hi> They have <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived much,</hi> and they make sutable <hi>Improvements</hi> and <hi>Returns.</hi> They are <hi>born of God,</hi> and they <hi>live to him.</hi> They have <hi>Treasures in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> and their <hi>Hearts are there.</hi> So that if you are sincere in your Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tensions, you will live like that <hi>pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar People</hi> who are chosen <hi>to shew forth the Praises of him who hath cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led you out of Darkness into his mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velous Light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>CONSIDER, <hi>my Brethren,</hi> God hath entrusted his <hi>Honour</hi> with you in a very special manner. And if you fall into Sin, your Defaults will wound the Repute of <hi>Religion,</hi> more than the Follies of many others. If you grow loose, or but remiss and luke-warm towards sacred Things, the Lovers of Sin will triumph,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:41862:74"/> not only over you, but over <hi>Religion</hi> it self.</p>
            <p>I cannot therefore do you a more valuable Kindness, than to call upon you to keep strictly to your <hi>Holy Purposes</hi> and <hi>Rules,</hi> and to mind you to embrace them with a Vigour like that of your <hi>first Love.</hi> You have run well hitherto, you have born a faithful Testimony against all Impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Immorality; and God hath directed your Steps by his Grace and Wisdom, so that ye have not given occasion to the Enemies of Vertue to speak reproachfully of you, or of it. <hi>O be not weary of well-doing; ye will reap speedily if ye faint not.</hi> You have but a little while longer to bear the <hi>Burden and Heat of the Day;</hi> and your Master's Eye is upon you all the while ye labour in his Vineyard, and will <hi>reward every one of you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your Works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WHILST you keep firm to your <hi>Religious Purposes,</hi> you will be sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by the Prayers and Suffrages
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:41862:75"/> of all good People; and the clearness of your own Consciences will chear you in the most adverse Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances: and what's above all, the Power and Consolation of the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> will sustain you in every Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and your End will be <hi>glorious.</hi> Whereas on the contrary, if you sink and swerve from your good Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, you will be the Grief of good People, the Scoff of the Wicked, the Contempt of the World, a Terror to your selves in all your serious Hours, especially in the Days of Trouble, and of Sickness, and Death; and alas! ye will be for ever pierced by the most dismal Regret, and Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condemnation, and be the Sport of mocking Devils to all Eternity.</p>
            <p>WHEREFORE, <hi>my Brethren,</hi> be <hi>zealously affected always in good Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; withdraw not your Hand from the Plough;</hi> but contend earnestly for that Crown of Righteousness which is prepared for them that love God. Let the Glorious Kingdom of
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:41862:75"/> our <hi>Lord Jesus Christ</hi> fill your Hearts and Minds; and then ye will pour a just Contempt upon the vain Things of this World, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite, but cannot treat a rational Soul with tolerable Satisfaction. We are taught, by the Sacred Word of God, to expect <hi>a Day, in which the Heavens will pass away with a great Noise, and the Elements will melt with fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Heat, and the Earth and all its Furniture be burnt up.</hi> Then will the whole Scene of visible Things be shifted; and <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Hell</hi> will divide all the Inhabitants of the Earth. O Sirs! let us live as it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes such a Faith: Since <hi>we expect such Things,</hi> let us convince the Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del World, that our Hearts are indeed set upon them.</p>
            <p>LET us often think, what a <hi>Glory</hi> it will be, to be embraced and own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by our Immortal and Illustrious King, the <hi>Lord Jesus Christ;</hi> to be acknowledged as his approved <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,</hi> to be embraced as his beloved
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:41862:76"/>
               <hi>Friends,</hi> and to be glorified as his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dopted <hi>Brethren;</hi> as those <hi>that have followed him in the Regeneration.</hi> This is the Honour, the Glory, the Bliss of Man. It is worthy of all the Care, and Sweat, and Sufferings that we can sustain in the pursuit of it. And this is the great, the sure, and the near Recompence of all the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Followers of the Lamb.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BE sure therefore, <hi>my Brethren,</hi> that ye walk in his blessed Steps, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly those of his <hi>Humility</hi> and <hi>Meekness.</hi> If the Leaven of Pride be found in you, it will corrupt all your other doings, and render you and your Works hateful in the sight of God. This Root of Bitterness is apt to take place in our Hearts; and ye can never be too careful to weed it out, nor too earnest in exalting the sweet and comely Grace of <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility.</hi> And if ye are <hi>meek, gentle,</hi> and <hi>patient towards all Men;</hi> ye will obtain many Triumphs over the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of Men by your <hi>submission,</hi> which
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:41862:76"/> would be exasperated by <hi>contempt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IN a word, be as submissive as ye have been to <hi>those that have the Rule over you,</hi> particularly to <hi>those who truly watch for your</hi> Souls; walk in Love one to another, as more than common Brethren; keep up to Chris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian <hi>Purity,</hi> regular <hi>Zeal,</hi> fervent <hi>Devotion,</hi> and an unblameable <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation;</hi> and then the Face of God will be towards you here, till at last it be opened to you in a rapturous Eternal Vision, through his <hi>beloved Son. Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <pb n="152" facs="tcp:41862:77"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Directions for Religious Conference, with PRAYERS for the use of <hi>Religious Societies,</hi> and upon other Occasions.</head>
            <p>I PREMISE that it may be very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient, and what would much promote the pious Design of these <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties;</hi> that an <hi>Orthodox and Pious Minister</hi> should be chosen by each So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, as the <hi>Director</hi> and <hi>Visiter</hi> of it; who may frequently be present at their Assemblies, to preserve Order, excite Zeal, and resolve Doubts.</p>
            <p>THIS would obviate many Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections concerning them, and would greatly benefit, countenance, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend such Assemblies.</p>
            <p>THIS <hi>Director</hi> may be chosen e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Year (when the <hi>Stewards</hi> are)
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:41862:77"/> by Majority of Votes (no manner of Salary or Reward being to be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on this Account) and when he is present, it will be his proper place to pray with the <hi>Society.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE Members of the <hi>Society</hi> are often to mind one another, to be very punctual to their Hour of Meeting; and to wave lesser Occasions that tend to divert them from coming to it. And when a competent Number of them are met; one of the <hi>Stewards,</hi> (if the <hi>Director</hi> be absent) or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Person desired, may begin the Conference thus: All standing up.</p>
            <p>MY Brethren, we are commanded of God, that <hi>our Communication be such as tends to the edifying of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and such as ministers Grace to the Hearers,</hi> Ephes. 4. 29. And we find the Spirit of God commending the Education of <hi>Timothy, That from a Child he had known the Holy Scriptures, which were able to make him wise unto Salvation, through Faith which is in
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:41862:78"/> Jesus Christ,</hi> 2 Tim. 3. 15. Let us therefore endeavour at this time to <hi>edify one another</hi> in the things of God, with the greatest Humility of Mind, and the tenderest Bowels of <hi>Christian Charity.</hi> For indeed, <hi>Wherewithal can a Young Man cleanse his way, but by taking heed thereto according to the Word of God?</hi> Psal. 119. 9. And that it may please God to instruct our Minds therein at this time, and to direct our Hearts and Lives thereby: Let us now put up our Prayers to God, (who is the <hi>Giver of all Grace,</hi> and the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of all Good) to accomplish this Holy Work in every one of us, by his <hi>Holy Spirit, for the sake of Jesus Christ his Son our Saviour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then the <hi>Steward</hi> may devoutly repeat these three Collects: All kneeling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Prevent us, O Lord, in all our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings with thy most gracious Favour, and further us with thy continual Help, that in all our Works begun,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:41862:78"/> continued, and ended in thee, we my glorify thy Holy Name, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally by thy Mercy obtain everlasting Life, through Jesus Christ our Lord.</p>
            <p>[<hi>All,</hi> Amen.]</p>
            <p>O Most Blessed Lord! who hast caused all Holy Scriptures to be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for our Learning; Grant, that we may in such wise hear them, read, mark, learn, and inwardly digest them; that by Patience and Comfort of thy Holy Word, we may embrace and ever hold fast the blessed Hope of everlasting Life, which thou hast given us in thy Son, our Saviour Jesus Christ. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O God! for as much as without Thee, we are not able to please thee; mercifully grant, that thy Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit may in all things direct and rule our Hearts, through Jesus Christ our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="156" facs="tcp:41862:79"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Then all rising, and seating themselves in their Places, the</hi> Steward <hi>may read one of the Chapters set down in the</hi> tenth Order; <hi>resting so long at the end of every Verse, that any one may have an Opportunity to make any serious Remark upon it. Or some part of an approved</hi> Exposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>on the</hi> Holy Scripture, <hi>or on the</hi> Catechism, <hi>may be read. And in order to a more advised Confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon the most important Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of our Holy Religion; the</hi> Steward (<hi>in the Absence of the</hi> Director) <hi>may, at the close of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Weekly Assembly, propose one of the following</hi> Subjects <hi>to be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coursed upon at their next Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference,</hi> viz.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. THE Duty of Self-examination, required 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 5.</item>
               <item>2. THE Duty of Self-abasement, and Self-renouncing, required <hi>Mark</hi> 8. 34.</item>
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:41862:79"/>
               <item>3. Faith in our Lord Jesus Christ, <hi>Mark</hi> 16. 16.</item>
               <item>4. Evangelical Repentance, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 10.</item>
               <item>5. Effectual Conversion to God, <hi>Acts</hi> 26. 18.</item>
               <item>6. Trust in God, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 17.</item>
               <item>7. Mortification, <hi>Rom. 8. 13. Gal.</hi> 5. 24.</item>
               <item>8. Humility, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 3. 2.</item>
               <item>9. Christian Hope, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 3.</item>
               <item>10. Christian Charity, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 1, &amp;c. Including the Love of God, <hi>Mark</hi> 12. 30. And the Love of Men, <hi>Ver.</hi> 31.</item>
               <item>11. Alms-deeds, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 1, 2, 3, 4.</item>
               <item>12. Contentment, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 11.</item>
               <item>13. Just-dealing, 1 <hi>Thess.</hi> 4. 6.</item>
               <item>14. Government of the Tongue, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12. 36, 37.</item>
               <item>15. Prayer and Praise, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>16. Chastity, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 27, 28.</item>
               <item>17. Temperance, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 25.</item>
               <item>18. Patience, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 20. 21, Meekness, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. 2.</item>
               <pb n="158" facs="tcp:41862:80"/>
               <item>19. The Publick Worship of God, <hi>Psalm</hi> 42. 2, 4.</item>
               <item>20. Heavenly-mindness, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 1, 2. And Contempt of the World, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 14.</item>
               <item>21. Of Christian Prudence, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. 16.</item>
               <item>22. Family-Duties, <hi>Josh.</hi> 24. 15. Or Religious House-hold Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, <hi>Acts</hi> 10. 2.</item>
               <item>23. Subjection to Magistrates, <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> 3. 1.</item>
               <item>24. Peace-making, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 9.</item>
               <item>25. Of Reproof, <hi>Lev.</hi> 19. 17.</item>
               <item>26. Sanctifying the Lord's Day, <hi>Numb,</hi> 15. 32, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>27. Growing in Grace, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 18.</item>
               <item>28. Improvement of Opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Doing and Receiving Good, <hi>Acts</hi> 10. 38.</item>
               <item>29. Duty of Parents and Children towards each other, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 6. 1, 2, 3. 4.</item>
               <item>30. Of the Husband and Wife, <hi>Ephos.</hi> 5. 22, to the end.</item>
               <item>31. Of Masters and Servants, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 6. 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.</item>
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:41862:80"/>
               <item>32. Of People to their Pastons, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 17.</item>
               <item>33. Of preparing for, and watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Performance of all Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Exercises, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 28, 29.</item>
               <item>34. The Duty of Christians to Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 17, 18, 19, 20, 21.</item>
               <item>35. Of endeavouring the Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion and Salvation of others, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 3, 4.</item>
               <item>36. The Sense of God's Omnipre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, <hi>Psalm</hi> 139.</item>
               <item>37. Of reading the Holy Scriptures, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. 6, 7, 8, 9. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16.</item>
               <item>38. Of Meditation, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 15.</item>
               <item>39. Of Circumspection, or Watch sulness, <hi>Mat. 24. 42, 43, &amp; 6.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>40. Of Perseverance, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 10. <hi>Jude, ver.</hi> 24.</item>
            </list>
            <p>THESE are Duties of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Importance, and are all su<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed to the Rules of these <hi>Societies.</hi> And I have kept to the number 40, that I might assign one distinct Subject of Discourse for every <hi>Weekly Conference</hi>
               <pb n="160" facs="tcp:41862:81"/> in the Year, reserving the Discourse of 12 of them to be spent upon the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of the Lord's Supper, which every Member is obliged by the Orders of the Society to receive (where he may with Conveniency) twelve times in the Year.</p>
            <p>THUS every Person knowing for a whole Week before, what will be the <hi>Subject</hi> of the Discourse at the next Conference, may the better prepare for it by sutable Reading, Meditation and Prayer.</p>
            <p>AND thus the chiefest parts of <hi>Christian Duty</hi> will be considered and gone thorow every Year, to the great Increase of Knowledg and Practice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note,</hi> THAT every Person is chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to bend his Discourse to further the <hi>Practice</hi> of every Duty, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Holiness of Life.</p>
            <p>AND it will be expedient, That no Person speak above 3 or 4 Senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, without a convenient Pause, to give room to others to speak their Mind. And in case of Silence, he may
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:41862:81"/> proceed, but with the same Caution.</p>
            <p>AND at the time of Conference, one of the <hi>Stewards</hi> (in the absence of the <hi>Director</hi>) may propose the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Questions,</hi> for the sake of Method; and that every ones Discourse may be the more directly practical, <hi>viz.</hi> when the Duty to be spoken to, is named, the Steward may say,</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. <hi>Quest.</hi> Wherein consists the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> of this Duty?</item>
               <item>II. <hi>Quest.</hi> What <hi>Directions</hi> do you propose in order to make the Practice of it more sure, and more easy?</item>
               <item>III. What <hi>Discouragements</hi> do any of you find in the Practice of it?</item>
               <item>IV. What <hi>Motives</hi> may encourage our Practice of this Duty, and our Perseverance in it?</item>
            </list>
            <p>IF the time permits, such Motives as these may be toucht upon, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The <hi>Authority</hi> of God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding.</item>
               <item>2. The <hi>Goodness</hi> of God, promising both to assist and reward the Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent.</item>
               <pb n="162" facs="tcp:41862:82"/>
               <item>3. The <hi>Terribleness</hi> of God's Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and the Examples of his Wrath sometimes seen upon Earth; and the dreadfulness of the <hi>everlasting Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> of an <hi>Almighty God,</hi> in the fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of his Wrath in the other World.</item>
               <item>4. The <hi>Excellency</hi> of the Duty it self.</item>
               <item>5. The <hi>Examples</hi> of Good Men, who have gone before us in the Ways of God.</item>
               <item>6. The Blessed <hi>Rest and Peace</hi> of a good Conscience; and the previous Hell of a bad one.</item>
            </list>
            <p>THESE general Heads may be the Method of Discourse upon any Duty at the Weekly Conference.</p>
            <p>THE Conference being ended, one of the Stewards may read some of the following Sentences, and the Admonition, to raise up and engage every Soul to <hi>Faith and Fervency</hi> in Prayer.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <pb n="163" facs="tcp:41862:82"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Directions suted to such Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Conference.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Sentences.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GOD is greatly to be fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Psal. 89. 7.</note>
                  <hi>in the Assemblies of his Saints; and to be had in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence by all that are about him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>GOD is a righteous Judg,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Psal. 7. 12.</note>
                  <hi>strong and patient; and God is provoked every day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>GOD will bring every Work</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccles. 12. 14.</note>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nto Judgment, with every se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret thing, whether it be good, or whether it be evil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>HE that hideth his Sins shall</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 28. 13.</note>
                  <hi>not prosper: but he that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesseth and forsaketh them, shall have Mercy.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="164" facs="tcp:41862:83"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>IF any Man sinneth, we have an Advocate with the Father,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Joh. 2. 1, 2.</note> Jesus Christ <hi>the Righteous; and he is the Propitiation for our Sins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O come, let us worship, and fall down, and kneel before the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Psal. 95. 6.</note>
                  <hi>Lord our Maker.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="admonition">
               <head>The Admonition before Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, to be read by the Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, (in the Director's Absence) if the time will permit.</head>
               <p>MY Brethren, since our gracious God has promised to be present, <hi>where two or thre<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> are gathered together in his</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 18. <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.</note>
                  <hi>Name:</hi> Let us duly conside<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> what an awful thing it is to draw nigh unto God; even to him who is <hi>able to save, or</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 12. 5.</note>
                  <hi>destroy us for ever:</hi> To him who sees our very Hearts and secret Thoughts, and who
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:41862:83"/> hath struck some Persons dead in the place, when they <hi>sought</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lev. 10. 2. 2 Sam. 6. 7. Numb. 16. 35. 1 Sam. 6. 19.</note>
                  <hi>him not in due order.</hi> As <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ab</hi> and <hi>Abihu, Ʋzzah, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ah,</hi> and many others.</p>
               <p>BUT we have a perfect and acceptable High Priest, the <hi>Lord Jesus Christ,</hi> who <note place="margin">Heb. 7. 26.</note> will perfect and present our Petitions to <hi>his Father, and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 20. 17.</note>
                  <hi>our Father,</hi> if we devoutly and sincerely serve him. And through this <hi>new and living</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 10. 19.</note>
                  <hi>Way</hi> we may approach to the Throne of Grace with an <hi>hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble boldness.</hi> Wherefore let us gird up the Loins of our Mind, and rouze up our drowsy Affections, and watch over our deceitful Hearts. <note place="margin">Jam. 1. 6.</note> Let us pray in Faith, and in Charity, with Fervency and <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2. 8.</note> Humility; considering that our present and future Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness depends upon our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing in Prayer. Let us
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:41862:84"/> therefore beseech God to assist us in this great Duty with his <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 26.</note>
                  <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> and thereby to help our Infirmities; and that he would graciously accept our unworthy Persons and Performances through his Son <hi>JESƲS CHRIST,</hi> whom he hath ordained to be a <hi>High Priest for ever, to make Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession for us.</hi> Amen. <note place="margin">Heb. 7. 25.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Let us pray.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <stage>Then all devoutly kneeling, they may join in this Confession of Sin.</stage>
               <p>ALMIGHTY God! Father of our Lord Jesus Christ; Maker of all Things; Judg of all Men: We ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg and bewail our manifold Sins and Wickedness, which we from time to time most grievously have committed, in Thought, Word and Deed, against thy Divine Majesty; provoking most justly thy Wrath and Indignation against us. We do ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:41862:84"/> desire to repent, and to be hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily sorry for these our Misdoings: The remembrance of them is grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous to us, the burden of them is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable. Have Mercy upon us, have Mercy upon us, most Merciful father! for thy Son our Lord Jesus Christ's sake, forgive us all that is past. And grant that we may ever hereafter, serve and please thee in newness of Life: To the Honour and Glory of thy Name, through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>OƲR Father which art in Heaven, hallowed be thy Name: Thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom come: Thy Will be done on Earth as it is in Heaven. Give us this day our daily Bread: And forgive us our Trespasses, as we forgive them that tres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pass against us: And lead us not into Temptation; but deliver us from Evil: For thine is the Kingdom, the Power, and the Glory, for ever and ever.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="168" facs="tcp:41862:85"/>
               <stage>Then the Steward alone may say,</stage>
               <p>ALMIGHTY and Everlasting God, who hatest nothing that thou hast made; and dost forgive the Sins of all them that are penitent: Vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe to create and make in us new and contrite Hearts, that we duly la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting our Sins, and acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Wretchedness, may obtain of thee, the God of all Mercy, perfect Remission and Forgiveness, through Jesus Christ our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="proceedings">
               <stage>Here may follow the Collect for the Day: And such other Collects in the Common-Prayer, as may be sutable.</stage>
               <stage>Then all rising.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Stew.</speaker>
                  <p>Glory be to the Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>All.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>As it was in the,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Stew.</speaker>
                  <p>Praise ye the Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>All.</speaker>
                  <p>The Lord's Name be praised.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="admonition">
               <pb n="169" facs="tcp:41862:85"/>
               <stage>Then the Steward may read the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Admonition to the Praise of God, before the singing of a Psalm, if time will permit.</stage>
               <p>LET us consider, my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, what cause we have <note place="margin">Psal. 100. 3.</note> to praise God. He is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of our Being; the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of our Mercies; the God of our Life and of our Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. O! praise the Infinite Goodness of God, <hi>who made</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Psal. 8. 5.</note>
                  <hi>us little lower than the Angels</hi> in the State of our Creation; yea, who hath shewn to us faln Men, more Compassion than to the faln Angels: for they are <hi>reserved in Everlast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jude 6.</note>
                  <hi>Chains of Darkness, to the Judgment of the Great Day;</hi> whilst we have the Offers of Eternal Redemption. And it pleases God to fit Men
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:41862:86"/> daily for his nearer Presence in the Work of Sanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whilst Devils are wholly <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 5.</note> given up to their malicious perverseness.</p>
               <p>LET us consider, That Man was made by God to be the Mouth of the Dumb Creatures in the Praises of their Creator: Man is to be the <hi>High Priest</hi> of the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Creation to offer up a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <note place="margin">Psal. 104.</note> Service for the whole Congregation of Sublunary Beings.</p>
               <p>LET us remember, That Man's <hi>Tongue is his Glory,</hi> a very <note place="margin">Psal. 57. 8.</note> wonderful and peculiar Gift of God to Men. Let us say therefore with the Holy <hi>Psalmist, I will greatly praise</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Psal. 109. 30.</note>
                  <hi>the Lord with my Mouth; yea, I will praise him among the Multitude.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="171" facs="tcp:41862:86"/>
               <p>LET us observe, with what chearfulness the very Birds tune their pleasant Notes to the Praise of their Maker af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their Capacity. <hi>They have</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 6. 26.</note>
                  <hi>no Store-house nor Barn,</hi> and know not where they shall find the next mouthful of Meat; yet how pleasant are they! And how void of Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murs or Sullenness.</p>
               <p>FINALLY, Let us consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that by praising God now, we learn how to praise God in Heaven. This will be the Work and Happiness of that State of Glory: Let <note place="margin">Rev. 19. 1.</note> us therefore join our sincere Praises in the Church below to those more perfect <hi>Hallelu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jahs</hi> of the Saints above. It is said, <hi>Rev. 14. 3. That none could learn their Song, but those that were redeemed from the Earth.</hi> From which we may
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:41862:87"/> note, that true Holiness is that which will fit us for the <hi>Songs of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>LET us therefore now strain up our Affections to the highest pitch; and so sing the Praises of God in Heart and Spirit, <hi>Psal.</hi> 148. 2. that <hi>Angels and Saints</hi> may join with us now, and we with them for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="proceedings">
               <stage>Then a Psalm may be sung; all stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up in this exalted part of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worship.</stage>
               <stage>Then may they repeat the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles Creed.</stage>
               <p>I <hi>Believe in God the Father Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, Maker of Heaven and Earth: And in Jesus Christ, his only Son our Lord; who was conceived by the Holy Ghost: Born of the</hi> Virgin Mary: <hi>Suffered under</hi> Pontius Pilate; <hi>was crucified, dead and buried: He
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:41862:87"/> descended into Hell: The third day he rose again from the dead: He ascended into Heaven, and sitteth on the right Hand of God the Father Almighty: From thence he shall come to judg the quick and the dead.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I believe in the Holy Ghost; The Holy Catholick Church; The Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Saints, The Forgiveness of Sins, The Resurrection of the Body, and the Life Everlasting.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>All.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lord, we believe; help thou our Ʋnbelief.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <stage>Then all kneeling. After the Collect, for Trinity Sunday, the Steward may proceed in Prayer for the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety,</hi> which may also be used in a private Family.</stage>
               <p>O Most Holy and Blessed God! The Creator, Governour and Judg of all; Who hatest Falshood and Hypocrisy, and wilt not accept the Prayer of feigned Lips; But <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="174" facs="tcp:41862:88"/> promised to shew Mercy to such as turn unto thee by true Faith and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance: Vouchsafe, we pray thee, to create in us clean and upright Hearts, through an unfeigned Faith in thy Son our Saviour. To us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed belongeth Shame and Confusion of Face: We are not worthy to lift up our Eyes or Voice towards Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; Our Natures are depraved, and our Ways have been perverse be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee. O! let not thy Wrath rise against us, lest we be consumed in a moment: But let thy merciful Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els yern over us; and vouchsafe to purify and pardon us, through thine All-sufficient Grace and Mercy in our Lord Jesus Christ. Since it hath pleased thee to offer him up as a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for Sinners, vouchsafe we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech thee to cleanse us from all Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity through his Blood. We be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that he is able to save to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termost those that come to thee by him; and we do earnestly desire to
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:41862:88"/> embrace him as our Prince and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour: O! give us Repentance and Remission of Sin through his Name. All we like Sheep have gone astray, every one in his own way: Good Lord, reduce us into thy Fold through this great Shepherd of Souls; and be pleased to lay on him the Iniquity of us all.</p>
               <p>AND as we have much to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given, be pleased to incline our Hearts to love thee much, who sorgivest Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, Transgression and Sin. Give us that Faith which worketh by Love, and such Love as will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strain us to have regard to all thy Commandments. And make us to look carefully to all our ways, that we may never again do any thing whereby thy Holy Name may be blasphemed, or thine Authority despised.</p>
               <p>GIVE us the deepest Humility, without which we can never be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of thee our infinitely conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scending
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:41862:89"/> God: Make us continually to tread in the Steps of our Blessed Lord and Saviour; being of a meek and quiet Spirit, always influenced by the highest Love of thee our God, and by the most charitable Dispositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons towards all Men.</p>
               <p>VOUCHSAFE to indue us with the saving Knowledg of Spiritual things, that we may receive all thy Truths in the love of them, in all Patience, Purity, Justice, Temper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, Godliness, and Brotherly-Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness; that we may adorn our Holy Profession, and resemble the Divine Goodness of thee our Heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>AND since we are not only weak and frail, but corrupt and sinful; vouchsafe, O Lord, to keep us by the Power of thine Holy Spirit, that we fall not from our avowed Sted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fastness in all Christian Duty. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve us from all the Sin and Vanity to which our Age, Condition, and
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:41862:89"/> Nature is prone, and to which the Devil and this World may at any time tempt us.</p>
               <p>GLORIFY, Good God, thy Strength in our Weakness, thy Grace in our Pollution, and thy Mercy in our Salvation. May our Holy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion be grounded and settled in our Hearts; that out of the good Treasure of a gracious Heart, our Speech may be savoury, and our Conversation exemplary; and that we may be fruitful in all good Works even to our old Age, and to our last day.</p>
               <p>FIT us we pray thee for every state of Life into which thy Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence shall cast us; prosper our law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Undertakings, preserve us Night and Day; and prepare us for a hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Death, and a Blessed Eternity.</p>
               <p>BE pleased, we beseech thee, to bless all those <hi>Societies,</hi> who in truth apply their Hearts to thy Service and Glory; we pray thee be pleas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:41862:90"/> to strengthen, stablish, and set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle both them and us in thy Faith, Fear, and Love.</p>
               <p>LET nothing in this World dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage us from the pursuit of those Holy Purposes, which thy Spirit has at any time put into our Hearts and Minds. But make us all faithful to thee our avowed God, and our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired Portion, even unto death; that we at last (with thy whole Church) may be partakers of that eternal Life and perfect Bliss, which thou hast promised, through Jesus Christ, thy only begotten Son, our only Mediator and Redeemer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="intercession">
               <pb n="179" facs="tcp:41862:90"/>
               <head>A General Intercession.</head>
               <p>ALMIGHTY God, whose King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Power is universal; Vouchsafe we pray thee to defend and prosper thy whole Church; and so dispose the Heart of thy Servant <hi>King William,</hi> that he may ever seek thy Honour and Glory. And grant to his whole Council, and to all in Authority under him, that they may truly and indifferently minister Justice to the suppressing of those Vices which reign amongst us, and to the reviving of true Religion and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord. And grant that all our Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops and Inferior Pastors may be effectually illuminated by the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of thy Word, that by their Holy Lives, and Sound Doctrine, they may convert many to Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness.</p>
               <pb n="180" facs="tcp:41862:91"/>
               <p>AND to all the People of these three Nations be pleased to give thy Heavenly Grace, that they may live in thy Faith and Fear, in Obedience to Authority, and in godly Love to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards each other.</p>
               <p>FINALLY, we commend to thy fatherly Goodness all those that are afflicted in Mind, Body or Estate, especially such as suffer for Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness sake. O Lord, relieve them according to their several Neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sities, give them patience under their Sufferings, and a happy Issue out of all their Afflictions; all which we beg in the Name and Mediation of Jesus Christ our Saviour. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="181" facs="tcp:41862:91"/>
               <head>A Thanksgiving.</head>
               <p>O MOST merciful God, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our Lord Jesus Christ, the inexhaustible Fountain of Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, we humbly praise thy Name for all thy Mercies vouchsafed to us. We praise thee, that thou madest us reasonable Creatures; that we were born in a Christian Land; and that we were early brought into thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Covenant. We bless thee for all the Advantages of our Educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for all the Benefits of good Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, and of seasonable Counsel and Reproof: For all the Comfort we have had in any Relation, Friend or Enjoyment, and for the comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Use of all thy good Creatures.</p>
               <p>WE praise thee for all the Benefits of Affliction; for thy merciful Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port in Trouble, and thy gracious
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:41862:92"/> Deliverances from any Evil.</p>
               <p>WE bless thy Name for our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Health, for our necessary Food, for our peaceable Habitations, and for that measure of outward things which thy Bounty hath dispensed to us.</p>
               <p>BUT above all, we bless and praise thy Name now (and desire to mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify thy Name for ever) for our Redemption by the Blood of thy Beloved Son; and that thou hast ordained Means of eternal Life thrô him.</p>
               <p>WE praise thee for thy Covenant of Life and Peace; for thy Word and Sacraments; for the Operations of thine Holy Spirit, and for any Evidence or Hope of thy Favour towards us, who are less than the least of thy Mercies.</p>
               <p>WE bless thee, Good God, for thy Patience towards us, for thy Calls to us, and for thy great Pity and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion to such unworthy Creatures.</p>
               <pb n="183" facs="tcp:41862:92"/>
               <p>SET home, we beseech thee, a due and constant Sense of these and all thy Mercies upon all our Hearts, and make us to live to the Praise of thee (the God of our Mercies) all our Days, through Jesus Christ our Lord, to whom with thee, and the Holy Ghost, be all Blessing, Honour, Glory and Power ascrib'd by Angels and Men for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="exhortation">
               <stage>Then all standing up, The following Exhortation to Humility may be read.</stage>
               <p>MY Brethren, since the Great God doth often assure us in his Holy Word, That <hi>he will resist the Proud,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">James 4. 6. 1 Pet. 5. 5.</note>
                  <hi>but give Grace to the Humble:</hi> Let us consider, that our Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings, tho never so good, will fail and come to nought, except we be <hi>truly and deeply</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 14. 11.</note>
                  <hi>Humble.</hi> Indeed it cannot be
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:41862:93"/> otherwise, because the proud Person quits his Reliance on God, to rest in himself, which is to exchange a <hi>Rock</hi> for a <hi>Reed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>ALAS! what are we, poor empty <hi>Nothings!</hi> yea, what is worse, condemned perish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">Gen. 32. 10.</note>
                  <hi>Sinners?</hi> We have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps Understanding now, but God can soon turn it into Madness: We may have some <note place="margin">Dan. 4. 42.</note> Attainments in Grace, but spiritual Pride will wither all, and soon reduce us to a very profligate and wretched State; such as we have seen others <note place="margin">Isa. 66. 2.</note> tumble into, who have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun in the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and ended in the <hi>Flesh. What have we that we have not received?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4. 7.</note> And which he that gave it, may not as soon take away?</p>
               <p>WE that are young in Years, and younger in Grace, <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3. 6,</note>
                  <pb n="185" facs="tcp:41862:93"/> are in danger of Self-conceit, and of being puffed up; which is a Quick-sand in which thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands have been swallowed up and perisht. It is not in vain, that the Apostle requires, <hi>That Young men be exhorted to be so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber-minded,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 16. 18.</note> Tit. 2. 6. which he elsewhere explains, when he says, <hi>Let no Man think of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Isa. 14. 12, 13.</note>
                  <hi>himself more highly than he ought to think, but to think so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly,</hi> Rom. 12. 3.</p>
               <p>BY Pride the Angels fell <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3. 6.</note> from Heaven: and if ever we climb up to those blessed Seats from which they are faln, it must be by the gracious steps <note place="margin">Luke 18. 14.</note> of Humility and Lowliness of Mind. <hi>Wherefore let him that</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10. 12.</note>
                  <hi>thinketh he standeth, take heed lest he fall. Let us walk hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly with our God,</hi> and with all Men; and ever have lowly Thoughts of our vile selves, <note place="margin">Rom. 11. 20.</note>
                  <pb n="186" facs="tcp:41862:94"/> and of our poor Attainments, and of our defective Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances: And with St. <hi>Paul, (who was in nothing behind the very chiefest Apostles)</hi> let us al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12. 11.</note> say, <hi>I am Nothing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>LET us therefore now sing to the Praise of God, to whom alone Praise is due.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="proceedings">
               <stage>Here sing a Psalm: After which the <hi>Steward</hi> may say;</stage>
               <p>IT is very meet and right, and our bounden Duty, that we should at all times, and in all Places, give thanks unto thee, O most blessed and bountiful God, in whose Hands our Breath is, and from whom cometh our Salvation.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>All.</speaker>
                  <p>Therefore with Angels and Arch-Angels, and with all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Heaven, we laud and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify thy glorious Name, evermore praising thee, and saying, Holy, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:41862:94"/> Holy, Lord God of Hosts! Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth are full of thy Glory. Glory be to thee O Lord most High. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Stew.</speaker>
                  <p>May the Grace of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Love of God, and the Fellowship of the Holy Ghost, be with us all evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Prayers for Families, for Seamen, and for young Persons.</head>
            <p>AT the Request of some under my Ministry, the following <hi>Prayers</hi> are added.</p>
            <p>And let it be noted, That the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Forms of Prayer and Praise may be properly used in <hi>Private Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies.</hi> And the Prefaces to both may be usefully read in Families now and then, to excite zealous Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:41862:95"/> and an awful dread of God in our Approaches to him.</p>
            <p>AND to the end, that the daily Worship of God may be set and kept up in every Family; let it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be forgotten, that the Spirit of God has denounced a most dreadsul Curse upon all prayerless Families: Jer. 10. 25. <hi>Pour out thy Fury upon the Heathen that know thee not, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Families that call not upon thy Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND, as I have often in my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, so I here again solemnly charge those that own my Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry, even in the Presence, and by the Authority of the Almighty God, that they pull not this denounced Curse upon themselves and Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies. And I again mind them to read the Word of God daily, and to <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techize</hi> their Children and Servants in a serious and effectual manner: and that they <hi>Remember the Lord's Day to keep it Holy,</hi> even the whole
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:41862:95"/> Day; and that they suffer not their Children or Servants to pollute any part of it, or trifle it away by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necessary worldly Business, or vain Discourse or Diversion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>These things are necessary to your Peace with God, and your dying in Hope.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for a Family in the <hi>Morning.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O MOST Holy and Blessed God! who fillest all Places with thy Presence, and art a searcher of all Hearts; with thee is terrible Majesty to confound thine Enemies, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Mercy to succour the humble and contrite Soul: we pray thee meet us not at this time in thy just Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance as a consuming Fire; but be pleased to accept us graciously through thy Mercy in our Lord Jesus Christ, who is our Hope.</p>
               <pb n="190" facs="tcp:41862:96"/>
               <p>WE have indeed lived too long as without God in the World; we have wickedly followed our own corrupt Desires and Devices; and have not duely owned thy Soveraignty and Dominion over us. We have broken our Vows, and stifled our Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and exceedingly defiled our selves, and offended thee, setting at nought the Promises and Threatnings of thy Book, and hating to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed. Lord, we lament our Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitency, and Unbelief, and all the sinful Fruits of our filthy and ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Hearts, Lips, and Lives. And we earnestly beseech thee, that thou wouldst not give us up to our own filthiness, and folly, and hardness of Heart: But that thou wouldst graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously reduce us into thy Fold and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, by the Power of thine Holy Spirit; and to accept and pardon us through the Merit of our Lord Jesus Christ.</p>
               <pb n="191" facs="tcp:41862:96"/>
               <p>AND, O Lord, vouchsafe to cleanse and sanctify us in Soul and Body; and make us to glorify thy Name on Earth, and to do the Work thou hast given us to do. Be pleased to subdue our Corruptions, and to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify every inordinate Affection and unruly Passion; and make us entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly resigned to thy Will, and subser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vient to thy Praise, now and ever.</p>
               <p>KEEP us, we beseech thee, from the Snares of worldly Pleasures and Enjoyments, and make us to set our Hearts on things above: And bring all the Powers of our Souls and Bodies into a willing subjection to thy Rule and Government. And save us from all carnal Ignorance and Unbelief, and from all Ungodliness, and sinful In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence of the Flesh.</p>
               <p>VOUCHSAFE, Good God, to pity our Weakness and Imperfection; and to succour us in all our Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and to support us in all our Sorrows and Afflictions: and grant
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:41862:97"/> us a happy end of all our Sorrows at last in thine eternal Kingdom.</p>
               <p>MAKE us ever mindful of the End for which we were made; and the chief Work we have to do; and the uncertainty of this present Life: and affect us duly by the forethought of that unchangeable Eternity to which we are hastening.</p>
               <p>AND let thy Faith and Fear ever dwell in our Hearts; that it may be our continual Exercise to keep our Consciences void of Offence both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thee our God, and towards all Men.</p>
               <p>SUFFER us not to spend the Day of our Salvation idely and unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly: But make us to work out our Salvation with Fear and Trembling, through thy Grace and Spirit; and make us to stand always upon our Watch, prepared for our Master's Call: That whensoever thou shalt put an end to this mortal Life, it may be the beginning of a Blessed Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality.</p>
               <pb n="193" facs="tcp:41862:97"/>
               <p>VOUCHSAFE, O Lord, to bless all our Governours in Church and State; and grant that they may be thy Ministers to us for Good, and that we may never be guilty of any sinful disobedience towards them. And give to all the People of this Nation, thy Grace to live in Unity and Godly Love, and to further each others present and eternal Welfare.</p>
               <p>BE pleased to bless all our Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Friends; and multiply thy Mercies upon them in the Blessings of this and of the other World: and vouchsafe to succor all that lie under any Sorrow or Affliction, and be near unto them in all they call upon thee for.</p>
               <p>MANIFEST thine especial Love and Favour, we pray thee, to this Family: Vouchsafe to provide for us, and defend us by thy good Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. Preserve us from all Evil throughout this Day; prosper us in our lawful Affairs; let no variance nor
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:41862:98"/> ill-will prevail amongst us, but keep us in Peace and Christian Love to our lives end.</p>
               <p>FINALLY, We praise thy great and glorious Name, for all thy Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies towards us: For the Rest and Safety of the last Night; for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed Comforts of this present Day, and all the good Providences of our past Life.</p>
               <p>MORE especially for the means of Grace, the motions of thy Spirit, and for thy great Patience and Long-suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering towards us. But above all, for the Merits and Mediation of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ, who ever liveth to make Intercession for us; for whose sake we beseech thee to hear us, accept us, and pardon us; together with these our unworthy Prayers; in whose most Holy Name and Words we further pray:</p>
               <pb n="195" facs="tcp:41862:98"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>OƲR Father which art in Heaven, hallowed be thy Name: Thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom come: Thy Will be done on Earth as it is in Heaven. Give us this day our daily Bread: And forgive us our Trespasses, as we forgive them that tres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pass against us: And lead us not into Temptation; but deliver us from Evil: For thine is the Kingdom, and the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and the Glory, for ever and ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for a Family in the Evening.</head>
               <p>O Eternal God! Infinite in all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and worthy of all Praise! who wilt be glorified in or upon eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Creature which thou hast made; It is meet, that with Fear and Trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, we consider thy holy and righteous Attributes, and our own polluted Natures and sinful Lives.</p>
               <pb n="196" facs="tcp:41862:99"/>
               <p>O Lord! we have sinfully forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten thee our Creator in the days of our Youth; and vainly mis-spent our precious time in Sin and Folly. Alas! with what diligence have we serv'd the Flesh, and the Devil, and this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent World! and how little have we minded the Concerns of our Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and eternal Life! We have not glorified thee the God that madest us, and in whose Hands our Breath is; but have lived as if we had been made only for this World, and to please our selves.</p>
               <p>O! how justly mayest thou snatch away our Breath from us, since we have so much abused it in idle and ungodly Speeches; and call us spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily into another World, since we have so presumptuously built our Hopes of Happiness in this! And should this be thy Pleasure and our Portion; O Lord, how could we appear before thee in the Guilt of thousands of unpardoned Sins! or
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:41862:99"/> how could we endure to dwell with everlasting Burnings!</p>
               <p>BUT with thee, O Blessed God, there is Infinite Mercy and Plenteous Redemption. Thou so lovedst the World, as to give thine only begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Son, that whosoever believes on him should not perish, but have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlasting Life. Lord, we desire to believe on him, help us we pray thee against our Unbelief. Enable us to submit all the Powers of our Soul to him in his saving Offices; and grant that we may so believe on him, that we may obtain Eternal Life through his Name.</p>
               <p>BE pleased to take away all Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purity and Hypocrisy, all insensible<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and perverseness from us; and make us thy willing and obedient Servants for ever. We know that without Holiness, none can enter into thy Kingdom: O Lord, make us Holy through the effectual Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and Sanctification of thine Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:41862:100"/> Spirit; that we may love thee with all our Heart and Soul, and serve thee with all our Might and Strength; and may delight to do thy Will, and to deny our selves for thy sake.</p>
               <p>AND since we have too long neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected that great Salvation, which was purchased for us by the Blood of thy Son; Awaken us, we pray thee, to improve the remaining space of our Days with all possible Care, giving all diligence to make our Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and Election sure.</p>
               <p>ENABLE us to break loose from the Snares of this present World, and from all the sinful Entanglements of the Flesh, and from the Seducements of wicked and dissolute Men; that we may run with speed that Race which thou hast set before us, and may persevere in it to the Death, that we may in the end attain ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting Life.</p>
               <pb n="199" facs="tcp:41862:100"/>
               <p>TO this end, make us habitually mindful of the shortness and uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of this Mortal Life, and the unprofitableness of all Earthly things in the Hour of Death, and in the other World. And make us now to choose thy Favour as our chiefest Good, thy Son as our Prince and Saviour, and thy Kingdom as our Portion. And when our Souls shall be summoned to leave this earthly Tabernacle, vouchsafe, Good God, to receive us into those everlasting Mansions which our Blessed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our has prepared for those that love Him.</p>
               <p>FOR whose sake, we pray thee, bless these three Nations with Plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Peace, and Safety, and with the Increase of all that's Good: And send Peace and Truth amongst all Nations.</p>
               <p>BE pleased to bless and direct all that are set in Authority over us; And grant that they may govern
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:41862:101"/> us, and we obey them, in the Fear of thee our God. Vouchsafe to suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour all that are Objects of Misery, whether they labour under Spiritual or Temporal Afflictions: And be pleased to administer to them as their Necessities of Soul or Body re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire.</p>
               <p>BE gracious to all our Relations and Friends, preserve them from all Evil, and bind up their Souls in the bundle of Life.</p>
               <p>BE more particularly gracious, we pray thee, to this Family, and to every particular Person it. Be pleas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to dwell with us, and rule over us: Preserve us in Peace and Safety; and let thy Spirit rule in every one of our Hearts, that we may faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully discharge our respective Duties one to another, and may live in Christian Union, Purity, and Peace. Vouchsafe, O Thou that never slum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berest nor sleepest! to grant us thy Protection this Night: Give thine
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:41862:101"/> Holy Angels charge concerning us: Preserve us from danger by Fire, and Tempest; and from the Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of unreasonable Men; and suffer no Evil to befal any of us, nor any Plague to come nigh our Dwellings.</p>
               <p>AND forasmuch as we know not whether we shall see the Light of another Day, be pleased, Good God, now to seal to every Soul of us the Pardon of all our Sins, through the Blood of the New Testament: That when we come to lie down upon our Death-Beds, we may rest in hope of a Blessed Resurrection.</p>
               <p>FINALLY, we laud and magnify thine Holy Name, O Lord, for thy Goodness in our Creation, and daily Preservation: For our Health, Ease, Peace, Friends, Food, Raiment, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverances, and all the Comforts of this present Life: And for all the Means of attaining everlasting Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness; for the Price which our Lord
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:41862:102"/> Jesus Christ has paid for our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption; for thy blessed Gospel, thine Holy Ordinances, and all the Motions of thy good Spirit: Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly imploring thy Grace, that we may so live to thy praise here on Earth, that we may at last be join'd with glorified Saints, and Holy Angels, to Praise thy Name for ever. All which we humbly beg for the sake of Jesus Christ our Lord and Saviour, in whose prevailing Name, and comprehensive Words, we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude our unworthy Prayers: <hi>Our Father,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="203" facs="tcp:41862:102"/>
               <head>A Prayer for a Person at Sea.</head>
               <p>O INVISIBLE and Omnipresent God! the Almighty Creator and absolute Governor of the whole World! Thou holdest the Winds in thy First, and givest Laws to the Sea which it cannot pass. My whole De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance is on Thee, from whom cometh my present Safety, and my eternal Salvation. I humbly beseech thee, for the sake of Jesus Christ thy Son, that thy Grace and Mercy may be with me all my Days.</p>
               <p>I have indeed dishonoured thy Name, despised thy Government, and broken thy Laws; I have often indulged my sinful Lusts and wrath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Passions, contrary to my Vows and Covenant made with thee, and thy Word revealed to us.</p>
               <pb n="204" facs="tcp:41862:103"/>
               <p>BUT, O Lord, for Christ's sake, (who is our Passover, slain for the Salvation of Sinners) be merciful un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, and pardon my Sins. Let not thy Wrath cut me off in my Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, as I have deserved; but let thy Mercy abound towards me for ever.</p>
               <p>AND vouchsafe, O Lord, to keep me by thy Grace, from the Sins to which I am daily exposed by Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and my own sinful Heart: And let thy good Providence preserve me from the Danger wherewith I am encompassed.</p>
               <p>WE behold, O Lord, thy Wonders in the Deep: Wonders of thy Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, as well as of thy Wisdom and Power: O Lord, give me Grace to admire and praise thine infinite Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections; and grant that my Lips may never blaspheme thy Great and Glorious Name, nor ever curse Men, who are made after thine Image and Likeness.</p>
               <pb n="205" facs="tcp:41862:103"/>
               <p>OUR times, O Lord, are in thine Hand; how soon mightest thou make this Sea a common Grave to us all? If but a Plank burst, or give way, or a Rock, or a Heap of Sand lie in our way, how soon shall we be swallowed up in the Deep, and be wafted into our endless and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable Estate?</p>
               <p>BUT thy good Providence is a sure Defence: I pray thee, vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe it to me, and to all that sail with me, in order to our continual Direction and Defence. And vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe to carry us in fafety to the Place of our Habitation, and to preserve all our Relations and Friends in their several Dwellings, that we may behold each others Faces again with Comfort.</p>
               <p>AND fit us all for that Place of Rest and Peace which thou hast pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised to thy faithful Servants; and give us thy Grace to make us meet for that eternal Inheritance amongst
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:41862:104"/> hy Saints, through Jesus Christ our Lord and Saviour, in whose Holy Name and Words we further pray; <hi>Our Father,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>In a Storm.</head>
               <p>O LORD our God! the Father of Mercies, the God of all Power and Might! Who commandest the Winds and the Seas, and they obey thee. We, O Lord, thy dependent Creatures, do send up our Cry unto thee in our Distress. O! let the Voice of our Prayers, and not the Cry of our Sins come before thee: Hear, we pray thee, the Intercession of thy Son for Sinners, and for his sake send us Relief.</p>
               <p>THERE is no Power in the whole Creation to help us. Lord, save us or we perish. Manifest, we pray thee, the greatness of thy Power in
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:41862:104"/> our Succour and Comfort, in the dark and deep Calamity wherewith we are distressed. The Winds and Waters know their Maker's Voice: and tho they are now in their Rage, yet if thine Almighty Voice speaks the Word, they will soon calm and be still. O Lord, be pleas'd to arise for our Help, that we may live to speak of thy Mercy, and tell of all thy Wondrous Works.</p>
               <p>AND, we pray thee, give us Grace that we may never forget nor abuse thy Mercy; but incline and enable us to live Holy, Righteous, and Sober Lives, to the Praise of thee our God, through Jesus Christ our only Mediator and Advocate. <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="208" facs="tcp:41862:105"/>
               <head>A Thanksgiving after a Storm.</head>
               <p>O LORD! Thou art the God of our Mercies, and the God of our Praise. I humbly present unto thee, O thou Preserver of Men! all possible Praise and Thankfulness for thy merciful and seasonable Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance for us in our late Distress. We said, we are cut off from the Living, and all our earthly Hopes are wither'd away; but thy good Providence ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd for us, and the Hand of our God brought us Deliverance from the Jaws of Death. Good Lord, enable us to comply with the end of thy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and Bounty towards us, and make thy present Mercy to us an invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable Band of future Obedience to thee, and an Earnest of thine everlasting Mercy to us, thrô Jesus Christ our Blessed Lord and Saviour. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="209" facs="tcp:41862:105"/>
               <head>A Thanksgiving when safely arriv'd at any Port.</head>
               <p>O INFINITELY Great and Good God! by whose good Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence I am brought in safety to my desir'd Haven; I humbly ascribe the whole of my Preservation and Success to thy Conduct and Blessing. It is not in the Power of Man to preserve himself, or to prosper his best Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours: but it is by thy Goodness that we live, and in which we hope. O Lord! give me thy Grace, that as I live by thee, I may live to thee, and may never more dishonour thy Name, or abuse thy Mercy; but may live such a Life of Praise to thee on Earth, as may be an Introduction to that state of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Bliss and Glory above, where Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Angels and Saints extol and praise thy Glorious Name for ever, through Jesus Christ our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="210" facs="tcp:41862:106"/>
               <head>A Prayer for a Young Person.</head>
               <p>MOST Glorious and Blessed God! The Life of our Life, and the God of our Salvation! I look up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Thee, the Fountain of Goodness, (through the Lord Jesus Christ, whom thou hast ordained to be our Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor) with humble Thankfulness for all the Mercies of this present Life, and for any Hope of everlasting Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness.</p>
               <p>IT is of thy great Goodness, that I was born in a Christian Land: and of thine infinite Mercy, that I was early brought into thy Covenant; thy Covenant of Life and Peace, through the Blood of the New Tes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tament.</p>
               <p>O my God! I desire to embrace the Engagements, as well as to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the Blessings of this thy gracious
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:41862:106"/> Covenant; earnestly imploring thy Grace, that I may live sutably to my Holy Profession: That so I may never, never dishonour thine Holy Name; nor in any Thought, Word or Deed, deny the Lord that bought me.</p>
               <p>SEND thine Holy Spirit, I beseech thee, into my Soul: Vouchsafe to regenerate and make me born anew of the Holy Ghost: Baptize me, O Lord, with that Divine Fire which may at once consume my sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Lusts, and enflame my Soul with Divine Love.</p>
               <p>LORD make me to know thee, and Jesus Christ whom thou hast sent: Prepare my Soul to receive him sincerely in all his saving Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices; and make him effectually to me a Prince and a Saviour, to give me Repentance and Forgiveness of Sin. Through Him, O Lord, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give my natural Corruption, and heal my Leperous Soul: And for
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:41862:107"/> his sake, forgive all my actual Sins; all the Transgressions of my Youth; my Sins after Vows, contrary to Knowledg, and against thine infinite Goodness. O Lord! for the sake of my Crucified Saviour, be merciful to my Unrighteousness, and remember my Iniquity no more.</p>
               <p>AND that I may no more commit the same, or other Offences; vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe, O Lord, to keep me by thy Grace from every sinful way, and lead me in the Way everlasting: Preserve me from the Pollutions of youthful Lusts; and harden me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Solicitations and evil Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of impudent and daring Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. Be pleased to shew me the vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of sensual Pleasures, the empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of worldly Possessions, and the Folly of getting any thing on Earth, by the loss of thy Favour. Bless me, O Lord, with an early Conversion, with an unblameable Life, with a hopeful Death, and a Blessed Eternity.</p>
               <pb n="213" facs="tcp:41862:107"/>
               <p>GIVE me, Good God, thy Peace which passeth Understanding; and so preserve me from the Corruptions of this World, that I may inherit the Glory of thine undefiled King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
               <p>AND whereas there are Legions of Infernal Powers, who seek to hinder my entrance into that Rest: O Lord, leave me not to their Malice, nor my own Frailty; but ever succour me with thine especial Grace and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Providence, and make me as ready to help, and to forgive others, as to desire help and forgiveness of thee my God.</p>
               <p>MAKE me to lead my Life in thy Fear, and in the sense of thy Favour, and to grow in Grace as I advance in Years; ever mindful of my Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, my Mortality, and my future Account: That living here to thy Glory, I may for ever praise thee in thy glorious Kingdom, through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ, who is my Hope; to
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:41862:108"/> whom with thee, O Father, and the Eternal Spirit, One God, be all Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Glory ascribed by Angels and Men for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notice_of_public_lectures">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>BY the Procurement of these <hi>SO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CIETIES,</hi> the following Lec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are constantly Preached at <hi>Five</hi> in the <hi>Evening,</hi> on the <hi>Lord's Days</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mentioned, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>On every first Lord's Day in the Month, at St.</hi> Laurence Jewry, <hi>St.</hi> Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Danes, <hi>St.</hi> Michael Woodstreet, <hi>St.</hi> Olaves Southwark.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>On the second Lord's Day in the Month, at St.</hi> Brides Fleetstreet, <hi>St.</hi> Albans Woodstreet, <hi>St.</hi> Buttolph Ald<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:41862:108"/>
            <p>
               <hi>On the third Lord's Day in the Month, at St.</hi> Martins in the Fields: <hi>at six in the Morning, St.</hi> Giles Cripplegate: <hi>Ʋpon every third Thursday in the Month, at</hi> Poplar, <hi>at six in the Evening.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>On the last Lord's Day in the Month, at St.</hi> Giles Cripplegate, <hi>St.</hi> Mary Whitechappel, <hi>St.</hi> John Wapping.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Every Lord's Day, at St.</hi> Ann's <hi>near</hi> Aldersgate, <hi>at five in the Evening; with publick Catechizing.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="erratum">
            <p>
               <hi>Errat.</hi> P. 163. read <hi>Chap. X.</hi> and for <hi>Directions</hi> read <hi>Devotions;</hi> which must likewise be noted over the following Pages.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:41862:109"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>TO rectify the Mistake of such as consider these <hi>Religious Societies,</hi> and the Promotion of the <hi>Reformation,</hi> as the Heat of <hi>young Persons</hi> only, which they think very likely to cool in a little time; I thought fit to subjoin: That I do not know any <hi>Religious Society,</hi> in which there are not seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral grave and prudent Persons, of solid Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and advanced Years from <hi>Forty</hi> to <hi>Sixty;</hi> which must indeed be the consequence of their having already continued above <hi>twenty</hi> Years. And they go on with great Vigour and Delight in the Ways of God, which they find to be <hi>Paths of Divine Pleasure,</hi> and the most <hi>solid Peace;</hi> which attracts many both young and elder Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons to them; perceiving their ways so strictly conform to the <hi>Laws</hi> of God and Men.</p>
            <p>And as to the <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> and other <hi>worthy Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons,</hi> who carry on the principal part of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation;</hi> they are of <hi>ripe Years</hi> and <hi>Experience,</hi> of considerable <hi>Quality</hi> and <hi>Estates,</hi> and of the best <hi>Character</hi> and <hi>Reputation.</hi> And indeed as the <hi>Honour</hi> of this Affair can never be call'd in question by any <hi>Devout Christian,</hi> so can it not at this time be treated with disrespect by any <hi>civil Person,</hi> since the <hi>KING,</hi> the <hi>Bishops,</hi> and some of the most <hi>Honourable Persons</hi> in Church and State, have solemnly espoused it, and declared for it.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:41862:109"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>